<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Finn Writes Movies</title>
  <subtitle>A place for my thoughts on movies and other writing.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/" />
  <updated>2025-04-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Finnlay Dall</name>
    <email>finnwritesdall@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>It Came from the Archives – Pig (2021)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/it-came-from-the-archives-pig-2021/" />
    <updated>2022-03-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/it-came-from-the-archives-pig-2021/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/aBXEONfn6MWD9UT3o44jBqWsjZW.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nicholas Cage caring for his truffle pig in the woods&quot;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Pig&lt;/em&gt; takes its time to get the simple things just right. There&#39;s no complicated pasts, no waffling sophistry and no drawn out scenes. This is not your three hour slow burn, this just ninety minutes of pure story. Where dialogue is absent, body language takes centre stage. It could be an assertive lean forward from Robin (Nic Cage) in Finway&#39;s, or a flinch from Amir (Alex Wolff) at the mention of his dad. The actors are allowed to breathe and really embody who they&#39;re playing. The dialogue that is present is dripping with subtext. Amir&#39;s hesitation to tell the truth about his mother&#39;s condition indicates what he truly wants for her. Additionally, when he asks Robin if he wants a camp shower, it seems like Amir only cares that his cash cow stay alive. However, by the second watch, it&#39;s clear that he has the capacity to care about other people, something his father lacks. All that can be extrapolated in one or two words of dialogue. Meanwhile, Cage doesn&#39;t need to say anything most of the time. Whether its visual or auditory clues like the tape from his wife or other characters troubles mirroring his own, his backstory has greater depth than if he were to explain it to anyone directly. Surprisingly, Wolff is able to hold his own against Cage, and the pair really elevate an already great narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s so much technically right with the film, it begs the question: Does it have anything to say? Portland, and other cities like it, toss the passionate aside in favour of those that perform. Robin was never one of those people. He clearly cares for his work, but due to societal pressure, has become a performer. Having lost his wife and growing distant from his family and colleagues, he decides he needs to make a change and moves to the wilderness. There he only has one responsibility, to take care of his truffle pig. He hates Amir because the young man reminds him of himself. A boy who cares, having to perform for his father. The idea of &amp;quot;staying power&amp;quot; is ever-present. Classical music, traditional films, literature all have staying power. However, what it does to people is a different matter. &#39;The show must go on.&#39; It makes baring it through gritted teeth the only option. The only option is to work at restaurant I hate for the rest of my life. The only option is to keep my vegetative wife on life support. I can suppress the grief, I can endure. There&#39;s a loss of soul. Robin has already learnt to put more care into his work, but what he&#39;s forgotten is how to take care of other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pig&lt;/em&gt;, is not without its flaws. The ending, felt a little too derivative of &lt;em&gt;Ratatouille&lt;/em&gt; to be considered &#39;grounded&#39; and the twist ending felt as though it robbed Robin of any catharsis; which unfortunately can&#39;t be elaborated on due to spoilers. Nevertheless, Michael Sarnoski&#39;s feature debut is a triumph that proves small stories handled with great care can make it onto the big screen.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It Came from the Archives – EO (2022)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/it-came-from-the-archives-eo-2022/" />
    <updated>2022-04-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/it-came-from-the-archives-eo-2022/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/egnCzNRjUzJGDQVorE7aWy0DFmi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;EO chilling with an Italian in a horse trailer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MC3A6JrWlGQ&quot;&gt;The Lincoln Centre&lt;/a&gt;, director Jerzy Skolimowski spoke of his early days as a filmmaker. Included was his utter shock in finding his first feature, &lt;em&gt;Walkover (1965)&lt;/em&gt;, achieved the second spot in Cahiers du Cinéma&#39;s annual top ten list. And what was his first instinct upon hearing such wonderful news? He rushed to the nearest cinema and watched the work of the man who bested him. That film, Robert Bresson&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Au Hasard Balthazar (1966)&lt;/em&gt;, was the first time the young upstart had wept at a piece of art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“EO”&lt;/em&gt; takes the character of Balthazar – once a metaphor for heroine Mary’s innocence – and puts the donkey centre stage. A mule for a performing circus, EO lives a quiet, content life with his handler Kasandra. However, bankruptcy and an uproar from activists soon forces the circus to pack up its tent; leaving all the animals to be re-homed. EO, now separated from the only person who truly loved him, must trek bravely across Poland to find her once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surreal visuals and a haunting classical score by composer Paweł Mykietyn, transports EO and the audience into a mythical re-imagining of the source material. Screenwriter Ewa Piaskowska went further back in time for her inspiration, citing stories like “&lt;em&gt;The Metamorphoses of Apuleius”,&lt;/em&gt; otherwise known as “&lt;em&gt;The Golden Ass”&lt;/em&gt;, to help define EO&#39;s journey. EO stumbles through a gnarled, gloomy forest, cold, scared and alone. As owls with sickly orange eyes glare down at him, hungry wolves stalk him through muddy waters and hunters take aim with laser sights at his neck, the audience grips their armrests, pulled into a Grimm with a capital G woods, hoping their little donkey friend will ever see the sun again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“EO”&lt;/em&gt; shines brightest when it leans into its fable roots. Skolimowski&#39;s direction, at its most raw and absurdist thanks to the editing of Agnieszka Glińska, finds itself right at home with some of Kafka&#39;s animal centred stories considering its strong themes of identity and belonging in a rigid and unjust world (&lt;em&gt;A Report for an Academy, Investigations of a Dog&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while excellent attention is paid to improving the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; of Bresson&#39;s original tragedy, &lt;em&gt;EO&lt;/em&gt; struggles to capture as meaningful a story as &lt;em&gt;Balthazar&lt;/em&gt; because every human character simply feels less thought out and disconnected from the main story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skolimowski wanted to do away with acts and focus on creating a non-linear narrative. But now with two screenings worth of context, unless you consider a meandering five act structure that literally goes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.johnyorkestory.com/about/the-book/&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Into the Woods”&lt;/a&gt; with occasional flashbacks and forwards &amp;quot;non-linear&amp;quot;, I don&#39;t see how you can reach that conclusion. Where characters in &lt;em&gt;Balthazar&lt;/em&gt; intersected and contributed to a modern portrait of The Seven Deadly Sins, the human characters of &lt;em&gt;EO&lt;/em&gt; feel shallow and lack the same crossover. Gerard and his mother’s confrontation, once a interesting scene of a parent cowardly enabling a monstrous teenage antagonist, has now been turned into some priest gambling away his family fortune and the not quite incestous relationship he has with his step-mother (What&#39;s this got to do with my donkey friend?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without this sense of connection, EO becomes less saintlike and more Satan like. A curse of red and black, that carries misfortune on his back for those unlucky enough to cross his path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“EO”&lt;/em&gt; is a visual and audible fairytale feast for the ears. However, as a response and homage to Bresson&#39;s original work, it struggles to have the same depth for its human characters as it does for its donkey.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Writing for Warmth</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/writing-for-warmth/" />
    <updated>2023-09-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/writing-for-warmth/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Currently, due to being hit by high gas bills at my rental, my roommates and I have decided to forgo heating altogether. While this works for them – being out of the house for work during the day and spending less time in an arctic fridge – working from home is an absolute nightmare. The thermostat read a room temp of twelve degrees on Wednesday morning (what a fun start to Spring). Of course, this self imposed suffering is just as much my decision as it is theirs (I refuse to heat a whole house just for my one room).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One great thing about having a cold room though is that it forces me out of the house and into some pretty nifty spaces. I ate at my usual café next to the station for lunch, enjoyed the sunlight, and instead of trudging to the library down the street to inhale stale air for three for hours, I plugged in my charger and parked myself in the comfortable booth of the café instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a cold heart that day as well as a cold body. I always have a lulling melancholy in the morning that gets in the way of my writing. Whether it’s guilt over not working on my own projects or feelings of rejection that leave me in a depressive state for several days, its a heavy burden on my workdays. But all that melts away with a warm coffee, friendly staff and a bit of metal blasting through my headphones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all these tragic circumstances I find myself thinking: what does it mean to write for one’s own betterment and not necessarily the audience’s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; (2023) as semi-autofiction.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/vxzcL7NuRonUqVRXMw60pXuhj7z.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scarlett Johansson looking out the window like I feel&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As annoying as it is to write, I wasn’t a big fan of Wes Anderson’s latest outing. Having seen it with other screenwriters was a fun time, but I got more out of the discussion afterwards than the actual film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPOILERS AHEAD FOR THE MOVIE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any fan will immediately recognise the ‘story within a story structure’ synonymous with the director’s work. The titular &lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; is, in fact, a costume rehearsal for the play written by the not so famous playwright, Conrad Earp. This black and white ‘reality’, complete with Bryan Cranston playing the role of a Rod Serling/Orson Welles style narrator, was the most interesting section; at least on a first watch. However, while it is fun to watch Anderson’s take of a “poorly” performed and unfinished play, to have it take up the majority of the runtime, risks an audience’s attention. A project with such dense visuals and dry humour becomes fatiguing to parse fairly over a two hour runtime. If its ‘movie to fake film’ ratio was something like &lt;em&gt;Cobweb (&lt;em&gt;Kim Jee-woon and not Samuel Boden)&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; where the finished shots were shown in snippets, I believe I would have been more receptive to what Anderson was trying to say about writing art in isolation. Instead, I was left with a reductive interpretation of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parallels between this small dustbowl town being locked off from the rest of society and the worldwide pandemic became obvious in retrospect. Even the playwright himself calls for a work that has his audience experiencing a “waking dream”, something that has been repeated ad nauseam these past three years. But why does Anderson choose to remind us of an event that we are, arguably, still trying to recover from?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all the lockdowns, zoom calls and premature deaths, the pandemic was a time for self-reflection. What else is there to do while stuck in your room except confront your life and the dark thoughts that come with doing that?For filmmakers, it seemed this same self-awareness was reflected both on screen and on the page. &lt;em&gt;Beau Is Afraid&lt;/em&gt; tried to bring the nightmares of a hypochondriac to life, the aforementioned &lt;em&gt;Cobweb&lt;/em&gt; had a director trying to scramble together a cast and crew under the noses of his superiors, and &lt;em&gt;The Fablemans&lt;/em&gt; was a literal mythologic retelling of Spielberg’s own life. While all these films are diverse in their genre, all of them delivered a self portrait of sorts; dealing with the self-doubting artist in one form or another. Beau’s doubt that he can make it on his own, director Kim’s doubt that he can surpass his predecessor, and Spielberg’s doubt that he can not only make it in the industry, but that he can make his parents proud of him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; continues this trend, as the actor, Augie Steenbeck, played lovingly by Jason Schwartzman, struggles to find the right angel for his character. Leaving amid a particularly climatic scene in the play, &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/CumVLUstblb&quot;&gt;he seeks the advice of the of play’s director (Adrien Brody), finding himself “lost” in the part.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes as a writer, getting it down and having your work out in the world is more important than worrying if it sounds good or if it makes any sense. If you’re doing it, you’re “doing [it] just right.” It’s vanity, the belief that you’re not meeting your own high standards or that your work is better or worse than someone else’s that stops writers from creating. What Anderson seems to be saying to both himself and other creatives is simply: get dirty. Enjoy your messy beauty! Grammar and punctuation be damned! Write to “keep telling [your] story” and lose all pretension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As much as I didn’t enjoy it as much initially, upon reflection, scenes like this give me hope for my own writing. Even if what I write lights my heart on fire and wells hot tears in my eyes, at least I’ll be warm.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Matinee Madness – Haunted Mansion (2023)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/matinee-madness-haunted-mansion-2023/" />
    <updated>2023-09-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/matinee-madness-haunted-mansion-2023/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/wUO1hjVCpMJMglsTWVDKN1qQsn5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The cast of Haunted Mansion (2023) looking about as horrified as a sack of wheat&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of to love about living a few doors down from your local cinema. One huge one is that on a whim - especially when eight dollar tickets are rumoured to roam the lobby halls - I can decide to sit down and watch a movie on the big screen. So, what better way to spend my sunshine filled morning than to lounge in a dark room for an hour or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arriving at around eleven, I had two choices for today. &lt;em&gt;Past Lives,&lt;/em&gt; the critically acclaimed debut from Celine Song, or yet another unnecessary Disney reboot; something I could have watched from home in a month’s time. Guess what my stupid arse picked?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s be fair, I didn’t want to immediately jump on the Disney hate train, I was hoping the stacked cast (Danny DeVito and Owen Wilson in the same picture!) would help carry most of the runtime. I was especially excited to see LaKeith Stanfield in a leading role again, as I absolutely adored him in &lt;em&gt;Sorry to Bother You (2018),&lt;/em&gt; and with the right director, he’s definitely capable of giving an otherworldly performance. But as unfortunate as it is to write, &lt;em&gt;Haunted Mansion&lt;/em&gt; is the film equivalent of a wad of melted candy: strange to look at and probably not safe to consume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t exactly criticise the visuals, as VFX artists don’t get paid enough for audience members to complain about shoddy CGI. If you want to complain, take it up with the execs. As long as it captured the jankiness of the original ride that’s all that mattered as far as I’m concerned. However, kids movie or no, I will never forgive its by the numbers storytelling. Powerful performances and monologues about lost loved ones are all well and good, but when its shoehorned exactly when it’s relevant and not when it’s needed creates a bland experience. And it seems Katie Dippold - or more likely the Disney execs that shadowed her - learned nothing from &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters (2016)&lt;/em&gt; (also an amazing cast poorly utilised).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it’s not enough to just have craft. You can be hitting all the beats and still not be making art. Arguably the film structure is “there” in the same way your dead grandma is “there” in the room with you. You feel them because you’ve been told to feel them. Stanfield has a dead wife and a future wife and son with a dead husband/Dad to fill the void by the end credits, but the dynamic feels obvious and transparent. And whose idea was it to make this film two hours? Thanks some lifeless craft we get all the information we need in the first ten minutes (although bizarrely they put the cold open of the mansion after Stanfield’s introduction). And those same plot points are stretched thinner than the white sheets on the mansion’s furniture. Granted, there are one or two jokes that break up the monotony, but the ones that raise more than a chuckle are far and few between.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The costumes and set pieces are the only saving grace, but even those are rushed by quicker than the titular ride. So, most of the film is spent sitting around denying the existence of ghosts, being scared of ghosts or crying over ghosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the film can tick all the boxes it wants, but it won’t capture hearts. And you might call me harsh for shitting on a corporate kids movie, but I don’t see Sony pulling any of this crap with the &lt;em&gt;Spider-Verse&lt;/em&gt; franchise. The way I see it, Disney had two reasons for releasing this. Either it was because they needed some straight to streaming slop in time for Halloween, or they were literally trying to create a movie for someone to fill in time while they wait in line on their phone for the real – ride. Either way, Both of us wasted a ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Slight Delay and a Slight Recommendation</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/a-slight-delay-and-a-slight-recommendation/" />
    <updated>2023-09-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/a-slight-delay-and-a-slight-recommendation/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I promised a weekly letter, so a weekly letter you’ll get. As penance for my lateness, please accept this review of a show I was lucky enough to find on Disney+.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heavenly Delusion&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tengoku Daimakyō&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/epSR5QO7CMgjNujvfCfCabiSJDN.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Maru and Kiriko in front of a Lovecraftian amount of viscera&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we march closer and closer to the singularity, it’s clear that future dystopias are on the rise again in science fiction. It’s become a bit tiring to see humanity’s end so many times. And you would be forgiven for missing out on &lt;em&gt;Heavenly Delusion,&lt;/em&gt; as its premise is also fairly simplistic. In a world of hellish monsters, a bodyguard is tasked with transporting the only child capable of destroying them. Their destination: “Heaven”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the show surprises from the first frame. Not only is the animation gorgeous – thanks to hardworking folks over at Production I.G – but the story is an elaborate web of twists and turns that keeps you guessing right up until the season’s jaw clenching ending. Its simplicity is a strength in disguise, as its vague setting provides space for the audience to piece things together themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes it does borrow a fair bit from &lt;em&gt;The Last of Us.&lt;/em&gt; Namely, its dynamic of ‘smuggler + smugglee makes family’ seems ripped straight from the game. But I think what’s admiring is that the creators knew what worked in that form of relationship and were able to create their own spin on it. For one, the age gap between Maru and his body guard, Kiruko is only about five years. This means the relationship between the two is more brother and sister than parent and child. This means the two characters are at once friends who can play around with each other, but still have the drama that comes with an overprotective sibling and rebellious teen pairing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Kiruko and Maru are the show’s main focus, we also get a glimpse into what “Heaven” is really like. A facility cut off from the outside in which super-powered are artificially reproduced and raised believing they are the future of humanity. That is, until they learn of the “outside of the outside”. This &lt;em&gt;Akira&lt;/em&gt; meets &lt;em&gt;Gattaca&lt;/em&gt; side story is a great compliment to the main plot thread as it has the audience wondering what will happen when the two groups meet, that is, if they ever do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does the world end with us, or the monsters we create?&lt;/em&gt; That seems to be the ultimate question posed by &lt;em&gt;Heavenly Delusion&lt;/em&gt;. And without getting into spoilers, it most definitely answers it more ways than one. There’s one particularly heartbreaking episode in which words on a smart tablet nearly brought me to tears; yes its that kind of show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing as it is an anime, there are one or two moments which might be a bit crass depending on how familiar you are with the format. But they are far and few between and do little to detract from the story being told. It also goes to some dark places fairly quickly, but if you were okay with &lt;em&gt;The Last of Us&lt;/em&gt; or anything similar you’ll probably be fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish I could dive deeper into the show without giving spoilers, but unfortunately like most TV nowadays, its better to go in knowing as little as possible. But if you do give it a shot, feel free to let me know! Trust me, you’re in for one hell of a ride!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Matinee Madness – Sick of Myself (2023)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/matinee-madness-sick-of-myself-2023/" />
    <updated>2023-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/matinee-madness-sick-of-myself-2023/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/lJXHuyY622HcA0RHJvkeJcvzamK.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kristine Kujath Thorp gobbling up black market pills from a kitchen table&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kristoffer Borgli creates a biting comedy of horrific proportions, as he explores narcissism in all its ugly glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film follows Signe, an aspiring painter who constantly struggles to wrestle attention away from her much more successful partner. After saving the life of dog attack victim at work – and coming off the high of being praised for her actions – she decides to research a way to disfigure herself, deciding that being a victim and surviving the trauma is a success story her sculptor boyfriend simply can’t beat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Signe, played beautifully by Kristine Kujath Thorp, is an abhorrent mess, she isn’t without sympathy. Eirik Sæther as Signe’s boyfriend, Thomas, seems to goad her at every opportunity and despite being just as insufferable as his girlfriend, he doesn’t catch nearly as much heat. From the beginning the film implies her vanity stems from a feeling of invisibility next to her male counterpart. Signe has to make herself feel physically sick, injure herself in order to take control of a room. Thomas just needs to speak up. It’s a subtle antagonism on display and I’m all here for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if the main message of this film was “toxic women really do have it hard” it would be insultingly skin deep. Instead, narcissism is portrayed as a self-destructive and malignant illness which festers inside the body. A side effect from defective pills she orders from Russia through her dealer, the skin lesions on Signe’s body begin as comical, yet aesthetically pleasing accessories to her act. But as they weep, bleed and swell, seemingly in response to her increasing lies, they force the film to take a sharp turn towards the grotesque and into the realm of gore and body horror. Her paranoid delusions often lead her away from seeking help. For example she aborts a brain scan simply because a vision tells her that the doctor will somehow deduce her nasty little secret and threaten to call the police. These visions are absurd and at times, hilarious but in the mind of a narcissist, they are all too reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film has its dark touches but is ultimately a comedy. I had to keep from laughing too loud as there were a few morning stragglers like myself, but believe me when I say it was a challenge. Slight spoilers ahead…but I never thought in my life I would see a sex scene and a funeral juxtaposed so brilliantly. That’s the great thing about Borgli’s direction: it’s shocking, downright nasty even, but it’s never crass. The gut punches are sudden, but they are not without warning. However, there are one or two moments where I feel things went too far or were a bit too on the nose. The selfie in the hospital, while funny, felt the obvious choice despite the film being up until that point quite reserved with its satire. And while the detox retreat was the perfect hell for narcissistic undesirables like Signe, I felt its dismissal of invisible disabilities to be in poor taste; and that’s coming from some one with a very visible one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sick of Myself&lt;/em&gt; is at once playful and horrifying yet never feels garish or simplistic in its portrayal of rotten people. So, I for one was ecstatic to learn that &lt;em&gt;Dream Scenario&lt;/em&gt; is already on its way to theatres and looks just as insane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q3x9iUL-74w&quot; alt=&quot;Dream Scenario Trailer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s all from me! Hopefully I’ll have more reviews in the future so stay posted!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Wonderful Story of Henry Sugar and The Swan (2023)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/the-wonderful-story-of-henry-sugar-and-the-swan-2023/" />
    <updated>2023-10-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/the-wonderful-story-of-henry-sugar-and-the-swan-2023/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/5WMIeZmsMQX3bArrcsoFJhUZIgr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Benedict Cumberbatch looking at you for help on how to play Blackjack at the casino&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strangely, my first encounter with Mr. Sugar wasn’t too dissimilar to how he discovers Dr. Chatterjee. I was about twelve years old, perusing the school’s library, “looking to see if [I] could find any of the sort of books [I] liked.” It was then, in the far corner of the fiction section, right down on the bottom left hand corner and “sticking out a little from the ones either side; I found the little green book that was to stick itself to the walls of my brain for the next thirteen years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first time I had read any of Dahl’s more mature stories. And reading it was like re-contextualising the life of an older relative after learning an, albeit harmless, truth. His twisted sense of humour, his insight into the horribleness of spoilt children and their parents, and his belief in the utter strangeness of life, all seemed to originate from these darker short stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wes Anderson, known for his own sense of whimsy and the auteur behind one of the most adored Roald Dahl adaptations of all time, seemed like the perfect choice to bring &lt;em&gt;The Wonderful Story of Henry Sugar&lt;/em&gt; to the silver screen. Naturally, when I saw Netflix’s trailer a month ago, I just had to grab a copy of the book to read it again. As of writing, I have watched both &lt;em&gt;Henry Sugar&lt;/em&gt; and the other piece that accompanied it in the book: &lt;em&gt;The Swan.&lt;/em&gt; Having now seen Anderson’s takes on these classic stories, was I disappointed? Yes and no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What didn’t disappoint were the fantastic hand crafted sets, the immaculate costumes and the quaint yet effective stop motion animations. I particularly liked how in both stories Roald Dahl himself, brought to life by the scarily similar Ralph Fiennes, plays the role of the narrator. What is especially interesting about these scene’s is that Anderson’s team painstakingly built an almost exact set of the author’s writing space. Dahl often went to a small hut behind his house to write. Cluttered with old maps and knick knacks, and completed by a simple lounge chair and make shift table, the space is very distinct compared to those of the library and café nomads like myself. As you can see from the comparison below, even the items hanging on the wall match up. It’s this kind of meticulous production design that sets Anderson apart from other directors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://austinkleon.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/dahl-writing-shed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ralph Finnes and Roal Dahl side-by-side&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, all of what I’ve just gushed about is typical Wes Anderson. What isn’t, and what irks me the most about these adaptations, is the rush to get through the stories as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is an awesome idea to literally read the stories line for line (Kip Williams’ &lt;em&gt;Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt; played with the same idea to great success) It’s best to give the actors time to really absorb and read the lines. But it seems Anderson, in attempt to be more playful and meta-textual, rushes through the stories at a frantic pace, as if the actors were forced to keep up with an audience that was rapidly losing interest. As scenes raced by, I felt more distracted than anything else. Before I could appreciate a scene I was whip panned to the next one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Swan&lt;/em&gt; suffered greatly from this. Ernie and Raymond, the two antagonists of the story, are supposed to slowly morph into these horrid monsters who would go as far as to kill one of their own classmates. Not only do we never see the boys in the short, we get to the climax, where the boys’ small violent acts have finally built up to them murdering their classmate, in mere minutes. The reader feels the torturous amount of time Peter spends in the clutches of his classmates, while the watcher feels little to nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted, reading the stories beforehand means I’m going to be much more critical of how the material was presented. However, when the titular swan is about to be killed, the narrator slows right down. Finally at the pen ultimate moment I could enjoy the genuine anger and horror emanating from the actors. Yes, who would have thought when the scenes were allowed to breathe that is when I felt most excited? But those moments were far and few between and at the worst of times, felt cut short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, the cutting of corners and rug pulls in &lt;em&gt;Henry Sugar&lt;/em&gt; made for some entertaining visual gags, (a reflective cube creating the illusion of levitation being my favourite) but &lt;em&gt;The Swan&lt;/em&gt; relying on an older and younger Peter to carry the whole story on their backs left me feeling sore. At least &lt;em&gt;Henry Sugar&lt;/em&gt; felt like it was adapting something. If I wanted someone reading these stories to me at 1.75x speed I would have put on the audiobook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s clear with &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:8080/writing-for-warmth/&quot;&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and now these shorts that Anderson wants to wear more of his influences on his sleeve, showing the seems of the production in his films. But I fear that while it matches the quirkiness of his previous films, breaking the fourth wall has only diminished the heart that used to be there. Performances that were once dry are now stilted, flattening once charming characters in the process. Whimsical worlds have now become amusement park rides. As beautiful as those sets are, if all the wires and stagehands are visible then all we are left with is the imitation, the fake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now don’t get it twisted, I still find Anderson to be an excellent director, and while I’m disappointed my two articles on the man are negative, I do still enjoy the detail and fun he puts into his production. That has at least stuck around for the most part. I just miss the sincere love he used to have for his characters. Maybe I’m blinded by nostalgia, so I wouldn’t mind going back to revisit some of his older films. Either he’s really changed or I have. And either way, I don’t think I’m going to be happy with the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! While this isn’t technically a Matinee Madness, I hope it was enjoyable nonetheless. May have more for you this week if you’re lucky, but otherwise, stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>We&#39;re All Going to the World&#39;s Fair (2023)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/we-re-all-going-to-the-worlds-fair-2023/" />
    <updated>2024-03-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/we-re-all-going-to-the-worlds-fair-2023/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/dY2hOaChOawRQnrcrEYiUVXqyoL.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Anna Cobb absolutely glowing with insanity&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Casey (Anna Cobb), a shy and nervy teen, begins her internet career like any other child her age: alone in her room, armed with nothing but some glow in the dark stickers and the preinstalled copy of Photo Booth that came with her Mac. Stumbling her way through awkward pauses and stealing panicked glances away from the camera, we learn the sole purpose of her channel: to document The World’s Fair Challenge. An alternate reality horror game that reports to physically change the player into someone, or something, else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane Schoenbrun creates an internet age that is at once, present, with TikTok lives of people documenting their ‘transformations’, and retrograde, with videos and personalities dedicated to exploring the world of creepypastas and SCP fan wikis. The use of mixed media, especially of antiquated tools like Skype and the aforementioned Photo Booth, bring to life a liminal space that, unlike &lt;em&gt;Skinamarink,&lt;/em&gt; feels not just out of place, but out of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anachronistic nature of the film allows the audience, not to be scared exactly, but to feel Casey’s isolation through the screen. For the film takes great pains to show Casey’s ** loneliness. A loneliness that has her desperately seeking some form of audience. Casey’s videos continually find her in spacious, often barren environments like her darkened bedroom or the projector room in the garage. The only time her father makes an appearance is as a disembodied voice, berating her for watching a music video at “three o’clock in the fucking morning.” It’s no wonder she takes part in the World’s Fair Challenge, because if it means her getting closer to people who actually care about her, she’ll take the risk. However, the more worrisome thought is that she took part in the challenge hoping that the ‘change’ being reported would finally help her feel something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Losing your sense of self is the greatest horror of &lt;em&gt;World’s Fair&lt;/em&gt; ; waking up one day to find you’re no longer in control of your body, or your mind. Early on in her journey, Casey admits to sleepwalking as a kid, describing the feeling as “watching [her]self on a TV all the way across the room,” and being “aware of [her] actions” but unable to “control [her]self.” Later, we see her completely transform. No longer stuttering or averting her eyes, Casey performs a dance number, embracing the camera’s gaze and singing with excited breaths. The shift in her mood invites an unease into the audience, who is used to her more timid self. This mood only worsens when she begins a sudden screaming fit, as if pulled out violently from a coma, before returning to her more bubbly, yet somehow more menacing, persona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disassociation has become a worrying trend in the era of screens, isolation and anti-social networks. That are our lives, much like the content we use to numb the pain of everyday, are becoming nothing more than a video, playing on a screen, in a dark room. The thought that our memories are nothing more than images in a collage or story, soon to be thrown away by the algorithm, fills my generation with dread. Even the connections we make to real, flesh and blood, humans aren’t safe, as JLB (Michael Rogers), the man who befriends Casey and tries to “protect” her, is implied to be an online predator, or at the very least, a parasocial stalker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film ends on a bleak note, with JLB’s final vlog recounting chance in-person meeting with Casey. It’s the only thing that tells the audience she’s not in harms way and comes off as nothing more than a lie told by a delusional middle aged man. Their are no good possible outcomes, as she’s either dead, presumed dead, or ultimately lost to &lt;em&gt;The World’s Fair.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the internet age contains many stories, each as inventive, and as dangerous, as the last. It’s easy to get caught up in some random wiki rabbit hole or listening to horror podcasts well into the witching hours. You can find yourself losing time and losing sleep. But always make sure to never lose yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! Apologies for the hiatus, this year’s been a real whirlwind! I’ll try to be covering more stuff in the coming months (including some of the Fantastic Film Festival program). As always, I appreciate the support and am always super chuffed when someone tells me they’ve been reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, if you ever want to go that extra mile…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry this not a segue into a monthly subscription. I would incredibly grateful if you’d get the word out about this newsletter. As I want to keep this up, but I also want to keep it &lt;em&gt;free.&lt;/em&gt; So, more eyes could mean more exclusive content (Reviews and essays for unreleased films or TV Shows, interviews, special segments).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I’ll still be writing away, so feel free to DM me on here, comment or email me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Fantastic Festival 2024</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/fantastic-festival-2024/" />
    <updated>2024-06-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/fantastic-festival-2024/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ticketing.oz.veezi.com/Media/Poster?siteToken=6d9jaxhwrpr635s3mt7t7yjbgc&amp;amp;code=0000005035&amp;amp;isHighRes=true&quot; alt=&quot;Fantastic Festival 2024 logo&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I promised I would do some coverage of this year’s Fantastic Film Festival, and while you’ll have to forgive me for my tardiness, I figured telling you a month later was a whole lot better than leaving you in the dark. So as a reward for being so patient, instead of one review, why not have three?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Sting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/k37Ccgu05Am1xxgN5GaW0HX9Kkl.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alyla Browne sleeping with a dangerous red-back looming over her head&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lido was packed for a pretty momentous opening night. There were friends of the filmmaker, local film critics and just those looking for a good creature feature to occupy their evening. Many dressed the part including Hudson, the artistic director of the festival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In full exterminator cosplay, with a huntsman stitched to his shoulder, he looked like he’d come straight from the set. Lido employees also took the opportunity to dress the theatre up, as cobwebs and toy spiders lined the corridors. Safe to say, there was a palpable energy in room. And carrying that same energy into the theatre, I was ready to enjoy my first night of this weird, wacky and wonderful festival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sting&lt;/em&gt; follows the story of Charlotte (Alyla Browne), a twelve year old New Yorker, who, under appreciated by her step father Ethan (Ryan Corr) and unable to go outside due to extreme snow storms, finds herself in a state of perpetual boredom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is until a tiny meteorite crashes through her bedroom window, and she comes face to face with her new friend: a red back spider from outer space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlotte raises the titular Sting on a diet of small bugs and insects. However, when it grows large enough to escape the confines of its jam jar, it begins to skulk the apartment vents, in search of a more substantial midnight snack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writer and director Kiah Roache-Turner wasn’t shy about his love for Ridley Scott’s &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt; and its influence on the film. From an environment on lockdown and the labyrinth of apartment vents, to the practical spider eggs bursting open to reveal gooey, flapping insides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having worked previously on the &lt;em&gt;Wyrmwood&lt;/em&gt; series and other Ozploitation projects, Roache-Turner wouldn’t have any trouble getting a monster movie off the ground. Nevertheless, considering his personal connection to the material and most of the writing stage taking place in lockdown, he knew he wanted to go above and beyond to make something special. So, snagging the opportunity to work with Wētā Workshop, most known for their involvement in &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; trilogy, to produce some of the classic creature designs, and finding the talented Alyla Browne just before she was to make her debut as a young Furiosa, all the pieces seemed to be in place to make cult classic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wētā Workshop knocked it out of the park. Sting shown in all its slimy, wet and shiny glory is truly what elevates the film from the straight to streaming slop you force yourself to put on in the background. That being said, I would hesitate to put this film up there with the other horror darlings of the past year – &lt;em&gt;Talk to Me, Late Night with the Devil and Evil Dead Rise&lt;/em&gt; just to name a few – as quite frankly the narrative elements were just uninteresting. While Ethan’s arc of learning to be a real father to Charlotte was a nice touch, it also lacked any depth or specificity. Conveying the reality of raising a daughter as a stepfather was clearly important to Roache-Turner, who was emphatic that this film was a monster movie ‘with heart’. Which would be fine if the father daughter relationship hadn’t felt so weak. Unlike &lt;em&gt;Evil Dead Rise,&lt;/em&gt; where the sometimes taut relationships of the characters would add to the tension in a given scene, it felt as if every dramatic scene in &lt;em&gt;Sting&lt;/em&gt; wanted to seperate itself from the ‘monster’ moments in an attempt to be treated more seriously. But when the dramatic writing has to also appeal to B-Movie standards, it just saps any excitement or tension from the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, it has to be written, but the decision to base the film in New York was a grave mistake. Imagine, having an all Australian cast, at a time when Aussie horror is making waves and having a giant, bloody red back spider as the monster, only to set the whole thing in America. The decision just doesn’t make sense. You could argue that like &lt;em&gt;Late Night with the Devil&lt;/em&gt; before it, the film needed its American setting for narrative reasons. After all, talk shows and snow storms are the two things Australians almost never bare witness to. I would argue a severe Melbourne or Sydney flood could offer the same, if not a better, “locked in” narrative device. However, during the Q&amp;amp;A, when asked about the choice to set it in the U.S, Roache-Turner said nothing of snow storms or floods, only citing the vague studio reason of ‘global appeal’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my misgivings about the choices made – both practically and narratively – &lt;em&gt;Sting&lt;/em&gt; was more fun than flat, and with some glorious kills interspersed throughout, it’s hard to stay mad at this local attempt at a creature feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Mars Express&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/5eGvv8fNk7tehTU5diwFY5cZRJM.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aline surround by allies and enemies on a pulp sci-fi inspired backdrop&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people outside Europe might be unfamiliar with french director and animator, Jérémie Périn. However, if you, like me, were old enough to access the internet in the 2010’s (hopefully all of you reading this were otherwise I might as well start calling myself an old man), you were either lucky, or perhaps unlucky enough, to bear witness to DyE’s &lt;em&gt;Fantasy&lt;/em&gt; music video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being an easily frightened child and only ever hearing it as “die fantasy” or “the fucked up” music video in and around the middle school locker room, I avoided seeing &lt;em&gt;Fantasy&lt;/em&gt; like the plague. But watching it now, there’s a clear artistry and thought behind the existential horror on display. And to think, roughly ten years after instilling fear into a generation of school children, Périn would come back with a full length animated feature worthy enough to premiere at the 76th Cannes film festival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aline (Léa Drucker), and her android partner Chris (Mathieu Amalric) are investigating the death of young computer science major and hacktivist, Jun Chow (Geneviève Doang). However, they’re soon dragged deeper and deeper down the rabbit hole when they discover that Jun had not only created a way to remove The Three Laws of Robotics from every machine, but that her subsequent murder was possibly carried out by someone in their precinct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mars Express’&lt;/em&gt; animation is just as fluid and gorgeous Perin’s previous work &lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; but it’s its commitment to going fully 3D that should honestly be commended. Despite the violence being somewhat toned down this time round, having characters with rigged models seemed to make the weight of what damage there was all the more impactful. There was a particular neck snap near the beginning that had me squirming in my seat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it does tend to borrow from the neo-noir science fiction that came before it ( &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner,&lt;/em&gt; and especially &lt;em&gt;Pluto),&lt;/em&gt; it’s thoughtful and rich world building is arguably what makes it stand out amongst the greats. The film chooses not to have a future defined by a human robot binary, instead the line is blurred. Humans have augmentations, androids are implanted with the digital backup of a human brain, and supercomputers are made with lab grown biomaterial. So, the question no longer becomes “who gets to be human?” but “who deserves to be free?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, if you were looking for a satisfying mystery, you’ll be left wanting. Don’t get the wrong idea, it starts off strong with a locked room style murder, and multiple suspects. However, it never felt like the audience was lead to the same conclusions the characters were. There’d be a major reveal and you’d wonder if you missed a clue or two. But seeing this with three other people, I can tell you that not one of us could remember anything being set up to prepare us for the wild finale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And speaking of that finale, while I won’t go into spoilers, it’s open ending left more questions than answers, and not in the good way that encourages rewatching the film, but in the way that they were pitching a sequel or TV series that would answer everything at a later date. A shame considering how excited I was to see an incredibly tight and self contained story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, it was no doubt one of my favourites at the festival and if Jérémie Périn and his talented team can make a miracle &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lepoint.fr/pop-culture/mars-express-un-rejouissant-spectacle-high-tech-22-11-2023-2544119*2920.php&quot;&gt;for under ten million euros&lt;/a&gt;, I eagerly await the next instalment in the &lt;em&gt;Mars Express&lt;/em&gt; cinematic universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Raid (2011)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/o3W687cfaQWTMHEga5offawNgED.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yayan Ruhian giving a bloodied Donny Alamsyah a good socking&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who takes their mum to see The Raid?&lt;/em&gt; That’s probably what some people were thinking as I sat down in the centre row with my fifty seven year old plus one. But knowing her love of Hollywood action movies and her propensity for the more boyish side of life, I had a feeling that the only barrier between her and the film would be the subtitle bar. And to no one’s surprise: she absolutely loved it. And to my surprise, I found myself not only liking it, as I’d had in the past, but now I simply adored it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was the energy of the audience, maybe it was seeing it on a massive cinema screen, or maybe it was every snap, crack and thump blasting through the &lt;em&gt;Dolby Atmos&lt;/em&gt; surround. Whatever it was, it had my heart racing and my eyes hooked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story’s quite simple. Rama (Iko Uwais) and several other MBC officers form a SWAT team to take down infamous drug lord, Tama Riyadi (Ray Sahetapy), who has occupied an apartment block to do his dirty work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rama and his superiors plan to catch Riyadi by surprise to keep the arrest clean and avoid any civilian casualties; knowing the criminal won’t hesitate to use his tenants as hostages. However, with every plan there’s always a contingency waiting to rear its ugly head. And when the unexpected death of a child lookout raises the building’s alarms, Rama and his sergeant, Jaka (Joe Taslim) will have to fight their way up and out if they want to survive, let alone arrest Riyadi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beautifully restored in 4K, its hard not to see why this indie action darling inspired the likes of &lt;em&gt;John Wick&lt;/em&gt; and the 2012 reimagining of &lt;em&gt;Dredd,&lt;/em&gt; the latter of which seems to take more than just a few plot points or shots of reference. Director Gareth Evans, clearly had an eye for what makes an action scene intense, as while there is a lot going on, the frame never once feels over or under crowded. Despite the breakneck pace, the audience is never bombarded. but still finds themselves wary of who or what might be lurking around the corner. His keen insight stems from his background as an action and stunt choreographer. No doubt this line of work would have lent itself to an appreciation of martial arts cinema. As every kick, punch and splatter is heard or seen. No action is left shredded on the cutting room floor. Every movement, from the ground floor all the way to the penthouse, is planned out in meticulous detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the copious amounts of kickboxing and hand to hand combat, their is also no shortage of every day weaponry. Wrenches, fluorescent lights and fridges filled with propane tanks; whatever you think would be on hand inside an apartment block, they use it. If you thought John Wick using a pencil was gnarly, just wait till you see what Rama does with a doorframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although my new found love for this film cannot be understated, I do find myself still critical of the twist ending, which, if you’ve seen the film isn’t exactly shocking. It’s the kind of ending that undercuts the stakes in an unsatisfying way rather than revealing anything new or mind-rattling. However, it is a small blemish on an otherwise simple, yet, strong narrative. It’s one of the few action films that sticks to the barebones demands of its genre, while still having effective protagonists, deep relationships and a menacing set of villains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a particular scene in which Mad Dog (Yayan Ruhian), Riyadi’s loyal henchman, backs Jaka into a corner by holding him at gunpoint. However, once inside one of the vacant apartments, he mockingly uncocks his pistol, skulks to the kitchen counter and places the magazine down. “I never liked using these,” he says before turning around to face Jaka, for him guns simply “take away the rush.” But as he spreads his fingers out in front his opponent in twisted glee, we know exactly what his weapon of choice is. By keeping dialogue simple and sparse, Evans may tell us less, but its clear that wants to show us a whole lot more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Raid&lt;/em&gt; is one of those sleeper hits in cinema that at least one person in your friendship circle knows about. And while over ten years of love and praise hasn’t quite helped it escape cult status into the mainstream. I think the best thing you can do right now is to see the restoration in cinema’s while it’s still floating around, or invite your friends for a movie night when the 4K release from Umbrella is available for purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for taking time to read. Hopefully you’ve now got some films to add to your watch-list. If you’d like to stay up to date on what else I’ve been watching lately, feel free to follow me over on &lt;a href=&quot;https://letterboxd.com/finnwritesdall/&quot;&gt;Letterboxd&lt;/a&gt;, as I’m fairly active (some would say &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; active) on there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, I’ll be writing some more stuff soon so stay tuned! And if you’re new here I would really appreciate any of you signing up for this newsletter, as it’s just nice to know my work is being seen by real eyeballs!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ghostlight  (2024) – The Whole Film&#39;s a Stage</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/ghostlight-2024-the-whole-films-a-stage/" />
    <updated>2024-10-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/ghostlight-2024-the-whole-films-a-stage/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/hNcM4VJOkcBZUtJTaMIsfBoUlcW.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A community theatre warmup exercise with Dolly de Leon in the middle&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having started this Substack over a year ago, and recently moving to yet another place that sits right next to a cinema, I thought that it was about time to post a more traditional review (Ah, just like old times). And what better movie to pick for the spookiest month of the year…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…than a cut and dry drama about a local theatre production in Chicago (Look, at least it has “ghost” in the title).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kelly O’ Sullivan and Alex Thompson return off the success of their 2019 film, &lt;em&gt;Saint Frances,&lt;/em&gt; to collaborate once more on &lt;em&gt;Ghostlight.&lt;/em&gt; A father and construction worker, Dan (Keith Kupferer) struggles to keep his head above water as he deals with a brash and antisocial teenage daughter (Katherine Mallen Kupferer), a fed up spouse (Tara Mallen) and the egregious fees from pursuing a lawsuit we don’t get the full details of until much later on. But his rage reaches a boiling point when he assaults a sports car revving douche for nearly running him over, and when his co-worker captures the whole thing on his phone (albeit regretfully), Dan’s left almost certainly out of a job. However, when local theatre actor, Rita (&lt;em&gt;Triangle of Sadness&#39;&lt;/em&gt;  Dolly De Leon) catches a glimpse of his pure emotion from across the street, she implores him to take part in a community theatre production of &lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt; in a desperate bid to replace one of their dropouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O’ Sullivan’s story seems to be a more overt love letter to dramaturgy, borrowing heavily from her time in the theatre. This extends to her casting of the three leads, who are not only long time collaborators onstage, but a legitimate family of thespians. It seems natural that a wife and husband theatre duo and their daughter, who was literally born in a theatre, should be the ones to play this bickering family of three. And while they live up to their parts, I fear the direction flattened their range to one of two emotions: reserved or explosive. &lt;a href=&quot;https://cinemafemme.com/2024/06/10/this-is-our-family-tara-mallen-keith-kupferer-and-katherine-mallen-kupferer-on-ghostlight/&quot;&gt;All three actors were worried about transitioning to the big screen,&lt;/a&gt; believing that they would struggle with the screenplay format and the edited world of performing in front of a camera, but found O’ Sullivan’s script and dialogue fit right at home on stage. As an actor, that’s great, but as an audience member, I couldn’t help but wonder if the dialogue, lacking in any form of subtext or tact, held me back from enjoying it. You can tell its bad when De Leon, who was a surprise gem in &lt;em&gt;Triangle&lt;/em&gt; and a natural in front of a camera &lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; was probably the weakest performance. Don’t get me wrong, Rita is fun and her weakness as a character has everything to do with the cookie-cutter role of ‘tired veteran’ she’s given. Nevertheless, ** conversations, tears and group hugs would always feel slightly soapy in execution, as everyone seemed to say exactly how they felt, even in moments of suppressed emotion. That’s not surprising, given that the film runs on the logic of a local stage production. Characters even repeat the same advice ad nauseam: on stage, it works to project emotions “for the people in the back.” Yet, when voices are mic’d up and amplified and performances are pulled into extreme focus, films like &lt;em&gt;Ghostlight&lt;/em&gt; , at least to me, deserve a much quieter touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By extension, a director needs a more adept hand. You can’t rely on flat compositions and basic blocking, which is unfortunately the case for eighty to ninety percent of &lt;em&gt;Ghostlight’s&lt;/em&gt; footage. School gyms are lit flatter than the deflated basketballs that tread on them, Daytime scenes look like they were shot on an iPhone (and not the Sean Baker kind with a kitted out rig either), while most emotional moments are either at a close up or establishing distance but are never in between. At least it didn’t &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; like a lifetime show, but that’s not a very high bar to clear for something that needed transcend a stage production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/fIhNqnVr8zP8RskAtRaBIHZzkB2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Katherine Kuperfer and Tara Mallen suffering through a messy hearing&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t mean to sound like a curmudgeon, as I’d be lying if I said I didn’t enjoy myself. But every time it would suck me in with it’s funny coincidences and cute father daughter bonding, it would blind me with its stage lights and have the ushers dragging me back out by my ankles. The worst instance being that pesky lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THIS IS YOUR SPOILER WARNING, HEED IT NOW OR EXPERIENCE A TRAGEDY MOST FOUL.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out Dan is essentially suing the family of his son’s girlfriend, who together with said son - pause for dramatic irony - committed a double suicide after not being able to see each other. Only, the girlfriend survived. So, Dan is convinced that the girlfriend drove him to do it. And it takes performing as Romeo (inhabiting a the mind of a character akin to his son), for him to forgive her and let go. As with most plays, this sounds on paper like the juiciest thematic twist, but in reality, feels like the thing in a first draft of a screenplay that you iron out to be just a little more plausible. For me, it literally would have made more sense for the girlfriend to be drink driving and surviving the crash, that way its similar enough to mirror &lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt; while still being different enough to feel a lot more grounded. It’s not lazy writing, but its one to one enough to definitely feel contrived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a lot of these same contrivances that really bring down the project for me, as you’ve got a template for a really special dramadey. They sting more than plot holes, because at least you can forgive a plot hole if everything else holds up. But contrivances, while they’re thematically relevant and sometimes necessary to keep a story’s momentum, always reek of the first and easiest option out of the possible beats a writer has listed out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the very least, the finale, much like the play itself, pulls its act together at the very last second, and while Dan’s sudden jump in stage proficiency is jarring. There are lavish costumes, moody lighting and tearjerking mise en scéne galore. The whole sequence where Dan performs Romeo’s final monologue as he catches visions of his son in wings, is stunningly realised. And while this continues when the family gets home in the gloomy hours of the night and the credits sneak their way in, its hard not to feel a little cheated. They held all of this beauty back for so long, it genuinely felt like they had just figured out how to make their stage production into a film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/rhy7zETGvG6f5bDtOSiE5k1j8cr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Keith and Katherine Kupferer performing Romeo and Juliet&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I do not want to end on a sour note. While I wasn’t blown away by the film itself, I had a great time watching this with an older crowd was a great. Everyone around me had a flurry of wonderful reactions, and shed a few tears at the end. It was hard not to get swept up alongside them. And if the players on the stage consider themselves a family, then I think, even if it’s just for a brief moment, the audience must be as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>