<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Finn Writes Movies</title>
  <subtitle>A place for my thoughts on movies and other writing.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/" />
  <updated>2025-08-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Finnlay Dall</name>
    <email>finnwritesdall@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>It Came from the Archives – Pig (2021)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/it-came-from-the-archives-pig-2021/" />
    <updated>2022-03-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/it-came-from-the-archives-pig-2021/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/aBXEONfn6MWD9UT3o44jBqWsjZW.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nicholas Cage caring for his truffle pig in the woods&quot;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Pig&lt;/em&gt; takes its time to get the simple things just right. There&#39;s no complicated pasts, no waffling sophistry and no drawn out scenes. This is not your three hour slow burn, this just ninety minutes of pure story. Where dialogue is absent, body language takes centre stage. It could be an assertive lean forward from Robin (Nic Cage) in Finway&#39;s, or a flinch from Amir (Alex Wolff) at the mention of his dad. The actors are allowed to breathe and really embody who they&#39;re playing. The dialogue that is present is dripping with subtext. Amir&#39;s hesitation to tell the truth about his mother&#39;s condition indicates what he truly wants for her. Additionally, when he asks Robin if he wants a camp shower, it seems like Amir only cares that his cash cow stay alive. However, by the second watch, it&#39;s clear that he has the capacity to care about other people, something his father lacks. All that can be extrapolated in one or two words of dialogue. Meanwhile, Cage doesn&#39;t need to say anything most of the time. Whether its visual or auditory clues like the tape from his wife or other characters troubles mirroring his own, his backstory has greater depth than if he were to explain it to anyone directly. Surprisingly, Wolff is able to hold his own against Cage, and the pair really elevate an already great narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s so much technically right with the film, it begs the question: Does it have anything to say? Portland, and other cities like it, toss the passionate aside in favour of those that perform. Robin was never one of those people. He clearly cares for his work, but due to societal pressure, has become a performer. Having lost his wife and growing distant from his family and colleagues, he decides he needs to make a change and moves to the wilderness. There he only has one responsibility, to take care of his truffle pig. He hates Amir because the young man reminds him of himself. A boy who cares, having to perform for his father. The idea of &amp;quot;staying power&amp;quot; is ever-present. Classical music, traditional films, literature all have staying power. However, what it does to people is a different matter. &#39;The show must go on.&#39; It makes baring it through gritted teeth the only option. The only option is to work at restaurant I hate for the rest of my life. The only option is to keep my vegetative wife on life support. I can suppress the grief, I can endure. There&#39;s a loss of soul. Robin has already learnt to put more care into his work, but what he&#39;s forgotten is how to take care of other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pig&lt;/em&gt;, is not without its flaws. The ending, felt a little too derivative of &lt;em&gt;Ratatouille&lt;/em&gt; to be considered &#39;grounded&#39; and the twist ending felt as though it robbed Robin of any catharsis; which unfortunately can&#39;t be elaborated on due to spoilers. Nevertheless, Michael Sarnoski&#39;s feature debut is a triumph that proves small stories handled with great care can make it onto the big screen.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It Came from the Archives – EO (2022)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/it-came-from-the-archives-eo-2022/" />
    <updated>2022-04-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/it-came-from-the-archives-eo-2022/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/egnCzNRjUzJGDQVorE7aWy0DFmi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;EO chilling with an Italian in a horse trailer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MC3A6JrWlGQ&quot;&gt;The Lincoln Centre&lt;/a&gt;, director Jerzy Skolimowski spoke of his early days as a filmmaker. Included was his utter shock in finding his first feature, &lt;em&gt;Walkover (1965)&lt;/em&gt;, achieved the second spot in Cahiers du Cinéma&#39;s annual top ten list. And what was his first instinct upon hearing such wonderful news? He rushed to the nearest cinema and watched the work of the man who bested him. That film, Robert Bresson&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Au Hasard Balthazar (1966)&lt;/em&gt;, was the first time the young upstart had wept at a piece of art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“EO”&lt;/em&gt; takes the character of Balthazar – once a metaphor for heroine Mary’s innocence – and puts the donkey centre stage. A mule for a performing circus, EO lives a quiet, content life with his handler Kasandra. However, bankruptcy and an uproar from activists soon forces the circus to pack up its tent; leaving all the animals to be re-homed. EO, now separated from the only person who truly loved him, must trek bravely across Poland to find her once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surreal visuals and a haunting classical score by composer Paweł Mykietyn, transports EO and the audience into a mythical re-imagining of the source material. Screenwriter Ewa Piaskowska went further back in time for her inspiration, citing stories like “&lt;em&gt;The Metamorphoses of Apuleius”,&lt;/em&gt; otherwise known as “&lt;em&gt;The Golden Ass”&lt;/em&gt;, to help define EO&#39;s journey. EO stumbles through a gnarled, gloomy forest, cold, scared and alone. As owls with sickly orange eyes glare down at him, hungry wolves stalk him through muddy waters and hunters take aim with laser sights at his neck, the audience grips their armrests, pulled into a Grimm with a capital G woods, hoping their little donkey friend will ever see the sun again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“EO”&lt;/em&gt; shines brightest when it leans into its fable roots. Skolimowski&#39;s direction, at its most raw and absurdist thanks to the editing of Agnieszka Glińska, finds itself right at home with some of Kafka&#39;s animal centred stories considering its strong themes of identity and belonging in a rigid and unjust world (&lt;em&gt;A Report for an Academy, Investigations of a Dog&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while excellent attention is paid to improving the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; of Bresson&#39;s original tragedy, &lt;em&gt;EO&lt;/em&gt; struggles to capture as meaningful a story as &lt;em&gt;Balthazar&lt;/em&gt; because every human character simply feels less thought out and disconnected from the main story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skolimowski wanted to do away with acts and focus on creating a non-linear narrative. But now with two screenings worth of context, unless you consider a meandering five act structure that literally goes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.johnyorkestory.com/about/the-book/&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Into the Woods”&lt;/a&gt; with occasional flashbacks and forwards &amp;quot;non-linear&amp;quot;, I don&#39;t see how you can reach that conclusion. Where characters in &lt;em&gt;Balthazar&lt;/em&gt; intersected and contributed to a modern portrait of The Seven Deadly Sins, the human characters of &lt;em&gt;EO&lt;/em&gt; feel shallow and lack the same crossover. Gerard and his mother’s confrontation, once a interesting scene of a parent cowardly enabling a monstrous teenage antagonist, has now been turned into some priest gambling away his family fortune and the not quite incestous relationship he has with his step-mother (What&#39;s this got to do with my donkey friend?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without this sense of connection, EO becomes less saintlike and more Satan like. A curse of red and black, that carries misfortune on his back for those unlucky enough to cross his path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“EO”&lt;/em&gt; is a visual and audible fairytale feast for the ears. However, as a response and homage to Bresson&#39;s original work, it struggles to have the same depth for its human characters as it does for its donkey.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Writing for Warmth</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/writing-for-warmth/" />
    <updated>2023-09-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/writing-for-warmth/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Currently, due to being hit by high gas bills at my rental, my roommates and I have decided to forgo heating altogether. While this works for them – being out of the house for work during the day and spending less time in an arctic fridge – working from home is an absolute nightmare. The thermostat read a room temp of twelve degrees on Wednesday morning (what a fun start to Spring). Of course, this self imposed suffering is just as much my decision as it is theirs (I refuse to heat a whole house just for my one room).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One great thing about having a cold room though is that it forces me out of the house and into some pretty nifty spaces. I ate at my usual café next to the station for lunch, enjoyed the sunlight, and instead of trudging to the library down the street to inhale stale air for three for hours, I plugged in my charger and parked myself in the comfortable booth of the café instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a cold heart that day as well as a cold body. I always have a lulling melancholy in the morning that gets in the way of my writing. Whether it’s guilt over not working on my own projects or feelings of rejection that leave me in a depressive state for several days, its a heavy burden on my workdays. But all that melts away with a warm coffee, friendly staff and a bit of metal blasting through my headphones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all these tragic circumstances I find myself thinking: what does it mean to write for one’s own betterment and not necessarily the audience’s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; (2023) as semi-autofiction.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/vxzcL7NuRonUqVRXMw60pXuhj7z.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scarlett Johansson looking out the window like I feel&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As annoying as it is to write, I wasn’t a big fan of Wes Anderson’s latest outing. Having seen it with other screenwriters was a fun time, but I got more out of the discussion afterwards than the actual film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPOILERS AHEAD FOR THE MOVIE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any fan will immediately recognise the ‘story within a story structure’ synonymous with the director’s work. The titular &lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; is, in fact, a costume rehearsal for the play written by the not so famous playwright, Conrad Earp. This black and white ‘reality’, complete with Bryan Cranston playing the role of a Rod Serling/Orson Welles style narrator, was the most interesting section; at least on a first watch. However, while it is fun to watch Anderson’s take of a “poorly” performed and unfinished play, to have it take up the majority of the runtime, risks an audience’s attention. A project with such dense visuals and dry humour becomes fatiguing to parse fairly over a two hour runtime. If its ‘movie to fake film’ ratio was something like &lt;em&gt;Cobweb (&lt;em&gt;Kim Jee-woon and not Samuel Boden)&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; where the finished shots were shown in snippets, I believe I would have been more receptive to what Anderson was trying to say about writing art in isolation. Instead, I was left with a reductive interpretation of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parallels between this small dustbowl town being locked off from the rest of society and the worldwide pandemic became obvious in retrospect. Even the playwright himself calls for a work that has his audience experiencing a “waking dream”, something that has been repeated ad nauseam these past three years. But why does Anderson choose to remind us of an event that we are, arguably, still trying to recover from?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all the lockdowns, zoom calls and premature deaths, the pandemic was a time for self-reflection. What else is there to do while stuck in your room except confront your life and the dark thoughts that come with doing that?For filmmakers, it seemed this same self-awareness was reflected both on screen and on the page. &lt;em&gt;Beau Is Afraid&lt;/em&gt; tried to bring the nightmares of a hypochondriac to life, the aforementioned &lt;em&gt;Cobweb&lt;/em&gt; had a director trying to scramble together a cast and crew under the noses of his superiors, and &lt;em&gt;The Fablemans&lt;/em&gt; was a literal mythologic retelling of Spielberg’s own life. While all these films are diverse in their genre, all of them delivered a self portrait of sorts; dealing with the self-doubting artist in one form or another. Beau’s doubt that he can make it on his own, director Kim’s doubt that he can surpass his predecessor, and Spielberg’s doubt that he can not only make it in the industry, but that he can make his parents proud of him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; continues this trend, as the actor, Augie Steenbeck, played lovingly by Jason Schwartzman, struggles to find the right angel for his character. Leaving amid a particularly climatic scene in the play, &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/CumVLUstblb&quot;&gt;he seeks the advice of the of play’s director (Adrien Brody), finding himself “lost” in the part.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes as a writer, getting it down and having your work out in the world is more important than worrying if it sounds good or if it makes any sense. If you’re doing it, you’re “doing [it] just right.” It’s vanity, the belief that you’re not meeting your own high standards or that your work is better or worse than someone else’s that stops writers from creating. What Anderson seems to be saying to both himself and other creatives is simply: get dirty. Enjoy your messy beauty! Grammar and punctuation be damned! Write to “keep telling [your] story” and lose all pretension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As much as I didn’t enjoy it as much initially, upon reflection, scenes like this give me hope for my own writing. Even if what I write lights my heart on fire and wells hot tears in my eyes, at least I’ll be warm.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Matinee Madness – Haunted Mansion (2023)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/matinee-madness-haunted-mansion-2023/" />
    <updated>2023-09-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/matinee-madness-haunted-mansion-2023/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/wUO1hjVCpMJMglsTWVDKN1qQsn5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The cast of Haunted Mansion (2023) looking about as horrified as a sack of wheat&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of to love about living a few doors down from your local cinema. One huge one is that on a whim - especially when eight dollar tickets are rumoured to roam the lobby halls - I can decide to sit down and watch a movie on the big screen. So, what better way to spend my sunshine filled morning than to lounge in a dark room for an hour or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arriving at around eleven, I had two choices for today. &lt;em&gt;Past Lives,&lt;/em&gt; the critically acclaimed debut from Celine Song, or yet another unnecessary Disney reboot; something I could have watched from home in a month’s time. Guess what my stupid arse picked?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s be fair, I didn’t want to immediately jump on the Disney hate train, I was hoping the stacked cast (Danny DeVito and Owen Wilson in the same picture!) would help carry most of the runtime. I was especially excited to see LaKeith Stanfield in a leading role again, as I absolutely adored him in &lt;em&gt;Sorry to Bother You (2018),&lt;/em&gt; and with the right director, he’s definitely capable of giving an otherworldly performance. But as unfortunate as it is to write, &lt;em&gt;Haunted Mansion&lt;/em&gt; is the film equivalent of a wad of melted candy: strange to look at and probably not safe to consume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t exactly criticise the visuals, as VFX artists don’t get paid enough for audience members to complain about shoddy CGI. If you want to complain, take it up with the execs. As long as it captured the jankiness of the original ride that’s all that mattered as far as I’m concerned. However, kids movie or no, I will never forgive its by the numbers storytelling. Powerful performances and monologues about lost loved ones are all well and good, but when its shoehorned exactly when it’s relevant and not when it’s needed creates a bland experience. And it seems Katie Dippold - or more likely the Disney execs that shadowed her - learned nothing from &lt;em&gt;Ghostbusters (2016)&lt;/em&gt; (also an amazing cast poorly utilised).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it’s not enough to just have craft. You can be hitting all the beats and still not be making art. Arguably the film structure is “there” in the same way your dead grandma is “there” in the room with you. You feel them because you’ve been told to feel them. Stanfield has a dead wife and a future wife and son with a dead husband/Dad to fill the void by the end credits, but the dynamic feels obvious and transparent. And whose idea was it to make this film two hours? Thanks some lifeless craft we get all the information we need in the first ten minutes (although bizarrely they put the cold open of the mansion after Stanfield’s introduction). And those same plot points are stretched thinner than the white sheets on the mansion’s furniture. Granted, there are one or two jokes that break up the monotony, but the ones that raise more than a chuckle are far and few between.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The costumes and set pieces are the only saving grace, but even those are rushed by quicker than the titular ride. So, most of the film is spent sitting around denying the existence of ghosts, being scared of ghosts or crying over ghosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the film can tick all the boxes it wants, but it won’t capture hearts. And you might call me harsh for shitting on a corporate kids movie, but I don’t see Sony pulling any of this crap with the &lt;em&gt;Spider-Verse&lt;/em&gt; franchise. The way I see it, Disney had two reasons for releasing this. Either it was because they needed some straight to streaming slop in time for Halloween, or they were literally trying to create a movie for someone to fill in time while they wait in line on their phone for the real – ride. Either way, Both of us wasted a ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Slight Delay and a Slight Recommendation</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/a-slight-delay-and-a-slight-recommendation/" />
    <updated>2023-09-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/a-slight-delay-and-a-slight-recommendation/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I promised a weekly letter, so a weekly letter you’ll get. As penance for my lateness, please accept this review of a show I was lucky enough to find on Disney+.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heavenly Delusion&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tengoku Daimakyō&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/epSR5QO7CMgjNujvfCfCabiSJDN.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Maru and Kiriko in front of a Lovecraftian amount of viscera&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we march closer and closer to the singularity, it’s clear that future dystopias are on the rise again in science fiction. It’s become a bit tiring to see humanity’s end so many times. And you would be forgiven for missing out on &lt;em&gt;Heavenly Delusion,&lt;/em&gt; as its premise is also fairly simplistic. In a world of hellish monsters, a bodyguard is tasked with transporting the only child capable of destroying them. Their destination: “Heaven”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the show surprises from the first frame. Not only is the animation gorgeous – thanks to hardworking folks over at Production I.G – but the story is an elaborate web of twists and turns that keeps you guessing right up until the season’s jaw clenching ending. Its simplicity is a strength in disguise, as its vague setting provides space for the audience to piece things together themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes it does borrow a fair bit from &lt;em&gt;The Last of Us.&lt;/em&gt; Namely, its dynamic of ‘smuggler + smugglee makes family’ seems ripped straight from the game. But I think what’s admiring is that the creators knew what worked in that form of relationship and were able to create their own spin on it. For one, the age gap between Maru and his body guard, Kiruko is only about five years. This means the relationship between the two is more brother and sister than parent and child. This means the two characters are at once friends who can play around with each other, but still have the drama that comes with an overprotective sibling and rebellious teen pairing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Kiruko and Maru are the show’s main focus, we also get a glimpse into what “Heaven” is really like. A facility cut off from the outside in which super-powered are artificially reproduced and raised believing they are the future of humanity. That is, until they learn of the “outside of the outside”. This &lt;em&gt;Akira&lt;/em&gt; meets &lt;em&gt;Gattaca&lt;/em&gt; side story is a great compliment to the main plot thread as it has the audience wondering what will happen when the two groups meet, that is, if they ever do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does the world end with us, or the monsters we create?&lt;/em&gt; That seems to be the ultimate question posed by &lt;em&gt;Heavenly Delusion&lt;/em&gt;. And without getting into spoilers, it most definitely answers it more ways than one. There’s one particularly heartbreaking episode in which words on a smart tablet nearly brought me to tears; yes its that kind of show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing as it is an anime, there are one or two moments which might be a bit crass depending on how familiar you are with the format. But they are far and few between and do little to detract from the story being told. It also goes to some dark places fairly quickly, but if you were okay with &lt;em&gt;The Last of Us&lt;/em&gt; or anything similar you’ll probably be fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish I could dive deeper into the show without giving spoilers, but unfortunately like most TV nowadays, its better to go in knowing as little as possible. But if you do give it a shot, feel free to let me know! Trust me, you’re in for one hell of a ride!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Matinee Madness – Sick of Myself (2023)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/matinee-madness-sick-of-myself-2023/" />
    <updated>2023-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/matinee-madness-sick-of-myself-2023/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/lJXHuyY622HcA0RHJvkeJcvzamK.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kristine Kujath Thorp gobbling up black market pills from a kitchen table&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kristoffer Borgli creates a biting comedy of horrific proportions, as he explores narcissism in all its ugly glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film follows Signe, an aspiring painter who constantly struggles to wrestle attention away from her much more successful partner. After saving the life of dog attack victim at work – and coming off the high of being praised for her actions – she decides to research a way to disfigure herself, deciding that being a victim and surviving the trauma is a success story her sculptor boyfriend simply can’t beat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Signe, played beautifully by Kristine Kujath Thorp, is an abhorrent mess, she isn’t without sympathy. Eirik Sæther as Signe’s boyfriend, Thomas, seems to goad her at every opportunity and despite being just as insufferable as his girlfriend, he doesn’t catch nearly as much heat. From the beginning the film implies her vanity stems from a feeling of invisibility next to her male counterpart. Signe has to make herself feel physically sick, injure herself in order to take control of a room. Thomas just needs to speak up. It’s a subtle antagonism on display and I’m all here for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if the main message of this film was “toxic women really do have it hard” it would be insultingly skin deep. Instead, narcissism is portrayed as a self-destructive and malignant illness which festers inside the body. A side effect from defective pills she orders from Russia through her dealer, the skin lesions on Signe’s body begin as comical, yet aesthetically pleasing accessories to her act. But as they weep, bleed and swell, seemingly in response to her increasing lies, they force the film to take a sharp turn towards the grotesque and into the realm of gore and body horror. Her paranoid delusions often lead her away from seeking help. For example she aborts a brain scan simply because a vision tells her that the doctor will somehow deduce her nasty little secret and threaten to call the police. These visions are absurd and at times, hilarious but in the mind of a narcissist, they are all too reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film has its dark touches but is ultimately a comedy. I had to keep from laughing too loud as there were a few morning stragglers like myself, but believe me when I say it was a challenge. Slight spoilers ahead…but I never thought in my life I would see a sex scene and a funeral juxtaposed so brilliantly. That’s the great thing about Borgli’s direction: it’s shocking, downright nasty even, but it’s never crass. The gut punches are sudden, but they are not without warning. However, there are one or two moments where I feel things went too far or were a bit too on the nose. The selfie in the hospital, while funny, felt the obvious choice despite the film being up until that point quite reserved with its satire. And while the detox retreat was the perfect hell for narcissistic undesirables like Signe, I felt its dismissal of invisible disabilities to be in poor taste; and that’s coming from some one with a very visible one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sick of Myself&lt;/em&gt; is at once playful and horrifying yet never feels garish or simplistic in its portrayal of rotten people. So, I for one was ecstatic to learn that &lt;em&gt;Dream Scenario&lt;/em&gt; is already on its way to theatres and looks just as insane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q3x9iUL-74w&quot; alt=&quot;Dream Scenario Trailer&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s all from me! Hopefully I’ll have more reviews in the future so stay posted!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Wonderful Story of Henry Sugar and The Swan (2023)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/the-wonderful-story-of-henry-sugar-and-the-swan-2023/" />
    <updated>2023-10-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/the-wonderful-story-of-henry-sugar-and-the-swan-2023/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/5WMIeZmsMQX3bArrcsoFJhUZIgr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Benedict Cumberbatch looking at you for help on how to play Blackjack at the casino&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strangely, my first encounter with Mr. Sugar wasn’t too dissimilar to how he discovers Dr. Chatterjee. I was about twelve years old, perusing the school’s library, “looking to see if [I] could find any of the sort of books [I] liked.” It was then, in the far corner of the fiction section, right down on the bottom left hand corner and “sticking out a little from the ones either side; I found the little green book that was to stick itself to the walls of my brain for the next thirteen years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first time I had read any of Dahl’s more mature stories. And reading it was like re-contextualising the life of an older relative after learning an, albeit harmless, truth. His twisted sense of humour, his insight into the horribleness of spoilt children and their parents, and his belief in the utter strangeness of life, all seemed to originate from these darker short stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wes Anderson, known for his own sense of whimsy and the auteur behind one of the most adored Roald Dahl adaptations of all time, seemed like the perfect choice to bring &lt;em&gt;The Wonderful Story of Henry Sugar&lt;/em&gt; to the silver screen. Naturally, when I saw Netflix’s trailer a month ago, I just had to grab a copy of the book to read it again. As of writing, I have watched both &lt;em&gt;Henry Sugar&lt;/em&gt; and the other piece that accompanied it in the book: &lt;em&gt;The Swan.&lt;/em&gt; Having now seen Anderson’s takes on these classic stories, was I disappointed? Yes and no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What didn’t disappoint were the fantastic hand crafted sets, the immaculate costumes and the quaint yet effective stop motion animations. I particularly liked how in both stories Roald Dahl himself, brought to life by the scarily similar Ralph Fiennes, plays the role of the narrator. What is especially interesting about these scene’s is that Anderson’s team painstakingly built an almost exact set of the author’s writing space. Dahl often went to a small hut behind his house to write. Cluttered with old maps and knick knacks, and completed by a simple lounge chair and make shift table, the space is very distinct compared to those of the library and café nomads like myself. As you can see from the comparison below, even the items hanging on the wall match up. It’s this kind of meticulous production design that sets Anderson apart from other directors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://austinkleon.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/dahl-writing-shed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ralph Finnes and Roal Dahl side-by-side&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, all of what I’ve just gushed about is typical Wes Anderson. What isn’t, and what irks me the most about these adaptations, is the rush to get through the stories as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is an awesome idea to literally read the stories line for line (Kip Williams’ &lt;em&gt;Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt; played with the same idea to great success) It’s best to give the actors time to really absorb and read the lines. But it seems Anderson, in attempt to be more playful and meta-textual, rushes through the stories at a frantic pace, as if the actors were forced to keep up with an audience that was rapidly losing interest. As scenes raced by, I felt more distracted than anything else. Before I could appreciate a scene I was whip panned to the next one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Swan&lt;/em&gt; suffered greatly from this. Ernie and Raymond, the two antagonists of the story, are supposed to slowly morph into these horrid monsters who would go as far as to kill one of their own classmates. Not only do we never see the boys in the short, we get to the climax, where the boys’ small violent acts have finally built up to them murdering their classmate, in mere minutes. The reader feels the torturous amount of time Peter spends in the clutches of his classmates, while the watcher feels little to nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted, reading the stories beforehand means I’m going to be much more critical of how the material was presented. However, when the titular swan is about to be killed, the narrator slows right down. Finally at the pen ultimate moment I could enjoy the genuine anger and horror emanating from the actors. Yes, who would have thought when the scenes were allowed to breathe that is when I felt most excited? But those moments were far and few between and at the worst of times, felt cut short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, the cutting of corners and rug pulls in &lt;em&gt;Henry Sugar&lt;/em&gt; made for some entertaining visual gags, (a reflective cube creating the illusion of levitation being my favourite) but &lt;em&gt;The Swan&lt;/em&gt; relying on an older and younger Peter to carry the whole story on their backs left me feeling sore. At least &lt;em&gt;Henry Sugar&lt;/em&gt; felt like it was adapting something. If I wanted someone reading these stories to me at 1.75x speed I would have put on the audiobook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s clear with &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:8080/writing-for-warmth/&quot;&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and now these shorts that Anderson wants to wear more of his influences on his sleeve, showing the seems of the production in his films. But I fear that while it matches the quirkiness of his previous films, breaking the fourth wall has only diminished the heart that used to be there. Performances that were once dry are now stilted, flattening once charming characters in the process. Whimsical worlds have now become amusement park rides. As beautiful as those sets are, if all the wires and stagehands are visible then all we are left with is the imitation, the fake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now don’t get it twisted, I still find Anderson to be an excellent director, and while I’m disappointed my two articles on the man are negative, I do still enjoy the detail and fun he puts into his production. That has at least stuck around for the most part. I just miss the sincere love he used to have for his characters. Maybe I’m blinded by nostalgia, so I wouldn’t mind going back to revisit some of his older films. Either he’s really changed or I have. And either way, I don’t think I’m going to be happy with the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! While this isn’t technically a Matinee Madness, I hope it was enjoyable nonetheless. May have more for you this week if you’re lucky, but otherwise, stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>We&#39;re All Going to the World&#39;s Fair (2023)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/we-re-all-going-to-the-worlds-fair-2023/" />
    <updated>2024-03-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/we-re-all-going-to-the-worlds-fair-2023/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/dY2hOaChOawRQnrcrEYiUVXqyoL.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Anna Cobb absolutely glowing with insanity&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Casey (Anna Cobb), a shy and nervy teen, begins her internet career like any other child her age: alone in her room, armed with nothing but some glow in the dark stickers and the preinstalled copy of Photo Booth that came with her Mac. Stumbling her way through awkward pauses and stealing panicked glances away from the camera, we learn the sole purpose of her channel: to document The World’s Fair Challenge. An alternate reality horror game that reports to physically change the player into someone, or something, else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane Schoenbrun creates an internet age that is at once, present, with TikTok lives of people documenting their ‘transformations’, and retrograde, with videos and personalities dedicated to exploring the world of creepypastas and SCP fan wikis. The use of mixed media, especially of antiquated tools like Skype and the aforementioned Photo Booth, bring to life a liminal space that, unlike &lt;em&gt;Skinamarink,&lt;/em&gt; feels not just out of place, but out of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anachronistic nature of the film allows the audience, not to be scared exactly, but to feel Casey’s isolation through the screen. For the film takes great pains to show Casey’s ** loneliness. A loneliness that has her desperately seeking some form of audience. Casey’s videos continually find her in spacious, often barren environments like her darkened bedroom or the projector room in the garage. The only time her father makes an appearance is as a disembodied voice, berating her for watching a music video at “three o’clock in the fucking morning.” It’s no wonder she takes part in the World’s Fair Challenge, because if it means her getting closer to people who actually care about her, she’ll take the risk. However, the more worrisome thought is that she took part in the challenge hoping that the ‘change’ being reported would finally help her feel something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Losing your sense of self is the greatest horror of &lt;em&gt;World’s Fair&lt;/em&gt; ; waking up one day to find you’re no longer in control of your body, or your mind. Early on in her journey, Casey admits to sleepwalking as a kid, describing the feeling as “watching [her]self on a TV all the way across the room,” and being “aware of [her] actions” but unable to “control [her]self.” Later, we see her completely transform. No longer stuttering or averting her eyes, Casey performs a dance number, embracing the camera’s gaze and singing with excited breaths. The shift in her mood invites an unease into the audience, who is used to her more timid self. This mood only worsens when she begins a sudden screaming fit, as if pulled out violently from a coma, before returning to her more bubbly, yet somehow more menacing, persona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disassociation has become a worrying trend in the era of screens, isolation and anti-social networks. That are our lives, much like the content we use to numb the pain of everyday, are becoming nothing more than a video, playing on a screen, in a dark room. The thought that our memories are nothing more than images in a collage or story, soon to be thrown away by the algorithm, fills my generation with dread. Even the connections we make to real, flesh and blood, humans aren’t safe, as JLB (Michael Rogers), the man who befriends Casey and tries to “protect” her, is implied to be an online predator, or at the very least, a parasocial stalker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film ends on a bleak note, with JLB’s final vlog recounting chance in-person meeting with Casey. It’s the only thing that tells the audience she’s not in harms way and comes off as nothing more than a lie told by a delusional middle aged man. Their are no good possible outcomes, as she’s either dead, presumed dead, or ultimately lost to &lt;em&gt;The World’s Fair.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the internet age contains many stories, each as inventive, and as dangerous, as the last. It’s easy to get caught up in some random wiki rabbit hole or listening to horror podcasts well into the witching hours. You can find yourself losing time and losing sleep. But always make sure to never lose yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! Apologies for the hiatus, this year’s been a real whirlwind! I’ll try to be covering more stuff in the coming months (including some of the Fantastic Film Festival program). As always, I appreciate the support and am always super chuffed when someone tells me they’ve been reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, if you ever want to go that extra mile…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry this not a segue into a monthly subscription. I would incredibly grateful if you’d get the word out about this newsletter. As I want to keep this up, but I also want to keep it &lt;em&gt;free.&lt;/em&gt; So, more eyes could mean more exclusive content (Reviews and essays for unreleased films or TV Shows, interviews, special segments).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I’ll still be writing away, so feel free to DM me on here, comment or email me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Fantastic Festival 2024</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/fantastic-festival-2024/" />
    <updated>2024-06-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/fantastic-festival-2024/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ticketing.oz.veezi.com/Media/Poster?siteToken=6d9jaxhwrpr635s3mt7t7yjbgc&amp;amp;code=0000005035&amp;amp;isHighRes=true&quot; alt=&quot;Fantastic Festival 2024 logo&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I promised I would do some coverage of this year’s Fantastic Film Festival, and while you’ll have to forgive me for my tardiness, I figured telling you a month later was a whole lot better than leaving you in the dark. So as a reward for being so patient, instead of one review, why not have three?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Sting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/k37Ccgu05Am1xxgN5GaW0HX9Kkl.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alyla Browne sleeping with a dangerous red-back looming over her head&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lido was packed for a pretty momentous opening night. There were friends of the filmmaker, local film critics and just those looking for a good creature feature to occupy their evening. Many dressed the part including Hudson, the artistic director of the festival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In full exterminator cosplay, with a huntsman stitched to his shoulder, he looked like he’d come straight from the set. Lido employees also took the opportunity to dress the theatre up, as cobwebs and toy spiders lined the corridors. Safe to say, there was a palpable energy in room. And carrying that same energy into the theatre, I was ready to enjoy my first night of this weird, wacky and wonderful festival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sting&lt;/em&gt; follows the story of Charlotte (Alyla Browne), a twelve year old New Yorker, who, under appreciated by her step father Ethan (Ryan Corr) and unable to go outside due to extreme snow storms, finds herself in a state of perpetual boredom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is until a tiny meteorite crashes through her bedroom window, and she comes face to face with her new friend: a red back spider from outer space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlotte raises the titular Sting on a diet of small bugs and insects. However, when it grows large enough to escape the confines of its jam jar, it begins to skulk the apartment vents, in search of a more substantial midnight snack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writer and director Kiah Roache-Turner wasn’t shy about his love for Ridley Scott’s &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt; and its influence on the film. From an environment on lockdown and the labyrinth of apartment vents, to the practical spider eggs bursting open to reveal gooey, flapping insides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having worked previously on the &lt;em&gt;Wyrmwood&lt;/em&gt; series and other Ozploitation projects, Roache-Turner wouldn’t have any trouble getting a monster movie off the ground. Nevertheless, considering his personal connection to the material and most of the writing stage taking place in lockdown, he knew he wanted to go above and beyond to make something special. So, snagging the opportunity to work with Wētā Workshop, most known for their involvement in &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; trilogy, to produce some of the classic creature designs, and finding the talented Alyla Browne just before she was to make her debut as a young Furiosa, all the pieces seemed to be in place to make cult classic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wētā Workshop knocked it out of the park. Sting shown in all its slimy, wet and shiny glory is truly what elevates the film from the straight to streaming slop you force yourself to put on in the background. That being said, I would hesitate to put this film up there with the other horror darlings of the past year – &lt;em&gt;Talk to Me, Late Night with the Devil and Evil Dead Rise&lt;/em&gt; just to name a few – as quite frankly the narrative elements were just uninteresting. While Ethan’s arc of learning to be a real father to Charlotte was a nice touch, it also lacked any depth or specificity. Conveying the reality of raising a daughter as a stepfather was clearly important to Roache-Turner, who was emphatic that this film was a monster movie ‘with heart’. Which would be fine if the father daughter relationship hadn’t felt so weak. Unlike &lt;em&gt;Evil Dead Rise,&lt;/em&gt; where the sometimes taut relationships of the characters would add to the tension in a given scene, it felt as if every dramatic scene in &lt;em&gt;Sting&lt;/em&gt; wanted to seperate itself from the ‘monster’ moments in an attempt to be treated more seriously. But when the dramatic writing has to also appeal to B-Movie standards, it just saps any excitement or tension from the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, it has to be written, but the decision to base the film in New York was a grave mistake. Imagine, having an all Australian cast, at a time when Aussie horror is making waves and having a giant, bloody red back spider as the monster, only to set the whole thing in America. The decision just doesn’t make sense. You could argue that like &lt;em&gt;Late Night with the Devil&lt;/em&gt; before it, the film needed its American setting for narrative reasons. After all, talk shows and snow storms are the two things Australians almost never bare witness to. I would argue a severe Melbourne or Sydney flood could offer the same, if not a better, “locked in” narrative device. However, during the Q&amp;amp;A, when asked about the choice to set it in the U.S, Roache-Turner said nothing of snow storms or floods, only citing the vague studio reason of ‘global appeal’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my misgivings about the choices made – both practically and narratively – &lt;em&gt;Sting&lt;/em&gt; was more fun than flat, and with some glorious kills interspersed throughout, it’s hard to stay mad at this local attempt at a creature feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Mars Express&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/5eGvv8fNk7tehTU5diwFY5cZRJM.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aline surround by allies and enemies on a pulp sci-fi inspired backdrop&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people outside Europe might be unfamiliar with french director and animator, Jérémie Périn. However, if you, like me, were old enough to access the internet in the 2010’s (hopefully all of you reading this were otherwise I might as well start calling myself an old man), you were either lucky, or perhaps unlucky enough, to bear witness to DyE’s &lt;em&gt;Fantasy&lt;/em&gt; music video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being an easily frightened child and only ever hearing it as “die fantasy” or “the fucked up” music video in and around the middle school locker room, I avoided seeing &lt;em&gt;Fantasy&lt;/em&gt; like the plague. But watching it now, there’s a clear artistry and thought behind the existential horror on display. And to think, roughly ten years after instilling fear into a generation of school children, Périn would come back with a full length animated feature worthy enough to premiere at the 76th Cannes film festival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aline (Léa Drucker), and her android partner Chris (Mathieu Amalric) are investigating the death of young computer science major and hacktivist, Jun Chow (Geneviève Doang). However, they’re soon dragged deeper and deeper down the rabbit hole when they discover that Jun had not only created a way to remove The Three Laws of Robotics from every machine, but that her subsequent murder was possibly carried out by someone in their precinct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mars Express’&lt;/em&gt; animation is just as fluid and gorgeous Perin’s previous work &lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; but it’s its commitment to going fully 3D that should honestly be commended. Despite the violence being somewhat toned down this time round, having characters with rigged models seemed to make the weight of what damage there was all the more impactful. There was a particular neck snap near the beginning that had me squirming in my seat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it does tend to borrow from the neo-noir science fiction that came before it ( &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner,&lt;/em&gt; and especially &lt;em&gt;Pluto),&lt;/em&gt; it’s thoughtful and rich world building is arguably what makes it stand out amongst the greats. The film chooses not to have a future defined by a human robot binary, instead the line is blurred. Humans have augmentations, androids are implanted with the digital backup of a human brain, and supercomputers are made with lab grown biomaterial. So, the question no longer becomes “who gets to be human?” but “who deserves to be free?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, if you were looking for a satisfying mystery, you’ll be left wanting. Don’t get the wrong idea, it starts off strong with a locked room style murder, and multiple suspects. However, it never felt like the audience was lead to the same conclusions the characters were. There’d be a major reveal and you’d wonder if you missed a clue or two. But seeing this with three other people, I can tell you that not one of us could remember anything being set up to prepare us for the wild finale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And speaking of that finale, while I won’t go into spoilers, it’s open ending left more questions than answers, and not in the good way that encourages rewatching the film, but in the way that they were pitching a sequel or TV series that would answer everything at a later date. A shame considering how excited I was to see an incredibly tight and self contained story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, it was no doubt one of my favourites at the festival and if Jérémie Périn and his talented team can make a miracle &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lepoint.fr/pop-culture/mars-express-un-rejouissant-spectacle-high-tech-22-11-2023-2544119*2920.php&quot;&gt;for under ten million euros&lt;/a&gt;, I eagerly await the next instalment in the &lt;em&gt;Mars Express&lt;/em&gt; cinematic universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Raid (2011)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/o3W687cfaQWTMHEga5offawNgED.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yayan Ruhian giving a bloodied Donny Alamsyah a good socking&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who takes their mum to see The Raid?&lt;/em&gt; That’s probably what some people were thinking as I sat down in the centre row with my fifty seven year old plus one. But knowing her love of Hollywood action movies and her propensity for the more boyish side of life, I had a feeling that the only barrier between her and the film would be the subtitle bar. And to no one’s surprise: she absolutely loved it. And to my surprise, I found myself not only liking it, as I’d had in the past, but now I simply adored it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was the energy of the audience, maybe it was seeing it on a massive cinema screen, or maybe it was every snap, crack and thump blasting through the &lt;em&gt;Dolby Atmos&lt;/em&gt; surround. Whatever it was, it had my heart racing and my eyes hooked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story’s quite simple. Rama (Iko Uwais) and several other MBC officers form a SWAT team to take down infamous drug lord, Tama Riyadi (Ray Sahetapy), who has occupied an apartment block to do his dirty work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rama and his superiors plan to catch Riyadi by surprise to keep the arrest clean and avoid any civilian casualties; knowing the criminal won’t hesitate to use his tenants as hostages. However, with every plan there’s always a contingency waiting to rear its ugly head. And when the unexpected death of a child lookout raises the building’s alarms, Rama and his sergeant, Jaka (Joe Taslim) will have to fight their way up and out if they want to survive, let alone arrest Riyadi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beautifully restored in 4K, its hard not to see why this indie action darling inspired the likes of &lt;em&gt;John Wick&lt;/em&gt; and the 2012 reimagining of &lt;em&gt;Dredd,&lt;/em&gt; the latter of which seems to take more than just a few plot points or shots of reference. Director Gareth Evans, clearly had an eye for what makes an action scene intense, as while there is a lot going on, the frame never once feels over or under crowded. Despite the breakneck pace, the audience is never bombarded. but still finds themselves wary of who or what might be lurking around the corner. His keen insight stems from his background as an action and stunt choreographer. No doubt this line of work would have lent itself to an appreciation of martial arts cinema. As every kick, punch and splatter is heard or seen. No action is left shredded on the cutting room floor. Every movement, from the ground floor all the way to the penthouse, is planned out in meticulous detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the copious amounts of kickboxing and hand to hand combat, their is also no shortage of every day weaponry. Wrenches, fluorescent lights and fridges filled with propane tanks; whatever you think would be on hand inside an apartment block, they use it. If you thought John Wick using a pencil was gnarly, just wait till you see what Rama does with a doorframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although my new found love for this film cannot be understated, I do find myself still critical of the twist ending, which, if you’ve seen the film isn’t exactly shocking. It’s the kind of ending that undercuts the stakes in an unsatisfying way rather than revealing anything new or mind-rattling. However, it is a small blemish on an otherwise simple, yet, strong narrative. It’s one of the few action films that sticks to the barebones demands of its genre, while still having effective protagonists, deep relationships and a menacing set of villains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a particular scene in which Mad Dog (Yayan Ruhian), Riyadi’s loyal henchman, backs Jaka into a corner by holding him at gunpoint. However, once inside one of the vacant apartments, he mockingly uncocks his pistol, skulks to the kitchen counter and places the magazine down. “I never liked using these,” he says before turning around to face Jaka, for him guns simply “take away the rush.” But as he spreads his fingers out in front his opponent in twisted glee, we know exactly what his weapon of choice is. By keeping dialogue simple and sparse, Evans may tell us less, but its clear that wants to show us a whole lot more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Raid&lt;/em&gt; is one of those sleeper hits in cinema that at least one person in your friendship circle knows about. And while over ten years of love and praise hasn’t quite helped it escape cult status into the mainstream. I think the best thing you can do right now is to see the restoration in cinema’s while it’s still floating around, or invite your friends for a movie night when the 4K release from Umbrella is available for purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for taking time to read. Hopefully you’ve now got some films to add to your watch-list. If you’d like to stay up to date on what else I’ve been watching lately, feel free to follow me over on &lt;a href=&quot;https://letterboxd.com/finnwritesdall/&quot;&gt;Letterboxd&lt;/a&gt;, as I’m fairly active (some would say &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; active) on there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, I’ll be writing some more stuff soon so stay tuned! And if you’re new here I would really appreciate any of you signing up for this newsletter, as it’s just nice to know my work is being seen by real eyeballs!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ghostlight  (2024) – The Whole Film&#39;s a Stage</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/ghostlight-2024-the-whole-films-a-stage/" />
    <updated>2024-10-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/ghostlight-2024-the-whole-films-a-stage/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/hNcM4VJOkcBZUtJTaMIsfBoUlcW.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A community theatre warmup exercise with Dolly de Leon in the middle&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having started this Substack over a year ago, and recently moving to yet another place that sits right next to a cinema, I thought that it was about time to post a more traditional review (Ah, just like old times). And what better movie to pick for the spookiest month of the year…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…than a cut and dry drama about a local theatre production in Chicago (Look, at least it has “ghost” in the title).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kelly O’ Sullivan and Alex Thompson return off the success of their 2019 film, &lt;em&gt;Saint Frances,&lt;/em&gt; to collaborate once more on &lt;em&gt;Ghostlight.&lt;/em&gt; A father and construction worker, Dan (Keith Kupferer) struggles to keep his head above water as he deals with a brash and antisocial teenage daughter (Katherine Mallen Kupferer), a fed up spouse (Tara Mallen) and the egregious fees from pursuing a lawsuit we don’t get the full details of until much later on. But his rage reaches a boiling point when he assaults a sports car revving douche for nearly running him over, and when his co-worker captures the whole thing on his phone (albeit regretfully), Dan’s left almost certainly out of a job. However, when local theatre actor, Rita (&lt;em&gt;Triangle of Sadness&#39;&lt;/em&gt;  Dolly De Leon) catches a glimpse of his pure emotion from across the street, she implores him to take part in a community theatre production of &lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt; in a desperate bid to replace one of their dropouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O’ Sullivan’s story seems to be a more overt love letter to dramaturgy, borrowing heavily from her time in the theatre. This extends to her casting of the three leads, who are not only long time collaborators onstage, but a legitimate family of thespians. It seems natural that a wife and husband theatre duo and their daughter, who was literally born in a theatre, should be the ones to play this bickering family of three. And while they live up to their parts, I fear the direction flattened their range to one of two emotions: reserved or explosive. &lt;a href=&quot;https://cinemafemme.com/2024/06/10/this-is-our-family-tara-mallen-keith-kupferer-and-katherine-mallen-kupferer-on-ghostlight/&quot;&gt;All three actors were worried about transitioning to the big screen,&lt;/a&gt; believing that they would struggle with the screenplay format and the edited world of performing in front of a camera, but found O’ Sullivan’s script and dialogue fit right at home on stage. As an actor, that’s great, but as an audience member, I couldn’t help but wonder if the dialogue, lacking in any form of subtext or tact, held me back from enjoying it. You can tell its bad when De Leon, who was a surprise gem in &lt;em&gt;Triangle&lt;/em&gt; and a natural in front of a camera &lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; was probably the weakest performance. Don’t get me wrong, Rita is fun and her weakness as a character has everything to do with the cookie-cutter role of ‘tired veteran’ she’s given. Nevertheless, ** conversations, tears and group hugs would always feel slightly soapy in execution, as everyone seemed to say exactly how they felt, even in moments of suppressed emotion. That’s not surprising, given that the film runs on the logic of a local stage production. Characters even repeat the same advice ad nauseam: on stage, it works to project emotions “for the people in the back.” Yet, when voices are mic’d up and amplified and performances are pulled into extreme focus, films like &lt;em&gt;Ghostlight&lt;/em&gt; , at least to me, deserve a much quieter touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By extension, a director needs a more adept hand. You can’t rely on flat compositions and basic blocking, which is unfortunately the case for eighty to ninety percent of &lt;em&gt;Ghostlight’s&lt;/em&gt; footage. School gyms are lit flatter than the deflated basketballs that tread on them, Daytime scenes look like they were shot on an iPhone (and not the Sean Baker kind with a kitted out rig either), while most emotional moments are either at a close up or establishing distance but are never in between. At least it didn’t &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; like a lifetime show, but that’s not a very high bar to clear for something that needed transcend a stage production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/fIhNqnVr8zP8RskAtRaBIHZzkB2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Katherine Kuperfer and Tara Mallen suffering through a messy hearing&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t mean to sound like a curmudgeon, as I’d be lying if I said I didn’t enjoy myself. But every time it would suck me in with it’s funny coincidences and cute father daughter bonding, it would blind me with its stage lights and have the ushers dragging me back out by my ankles. The worst instance being that pesky lawsuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THIS IS YOUR SPOILER WARNING, HEED IT NOW OR EXPERIENCE A TRAGEDY MOST FOUL.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out Dan is essentially suing the family of his son’s girlfriend, who together with said son - pause for dramatic irony - committed a double suicide after not being able to see each other. Only, the girlfriend survived. So, Dan is convinced that the girlfriend drove him to do it. And it takes performing as Romeo (inhabiting a the mind of a character akin to his son), for him to forgive her and let go. As with most plays, this sounds on paper like the juiciest thematic twist, but in reality, feels like the thing in a first draft of a screenplay that you iron out to be just a little more plausible. For me, it literally would have made more sense for the girlfriend to be drink driving and surviving the crash, that way its similar enough to mirror &lt;em&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/em&gt; while still being different enough to feel a lot more grounded. It’s not lazy writing, but its one to one enough to definitely feel contrived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a lot of these same contrivances that really bring down the project for me, as you’ve got a template for a really special dramadey. They sting more than plot holes, because at least you can forgive a plot hole if everything else holds up. But contrivances, while they’re thematically relevant and sometimes necessary to keep a story’s momentum, always reek of the first and easiest option out of the possible beats a writer has listed out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the very least, the finale, much like the play itself, pulls its act together at the very last second, and while Dan’s sudden jump in stage proficiency is jarring. There are lavish costumes, moody lighting and tearjerking mise en scéne galore. The whole sequence where Dan performs Romeo’s final monologue as he catches visions of his son in wings, is stunningly realised. And while this continues when the family gets home in the gloomy hours of the night and the credits sneak their way in, its hard not to feel a little cheated. They held all of this beauty back for so long, it genuinely felt like they had just figured out how to make their stage production into a film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/rhy7zETGvG6f5bDtOSiE5k1j8cr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Keith and Katherine Kupferer performing Romeo and Juliet&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I do not want to end on a sour note. While I wasn’t blown away by the film itself, I had a great time watching this with an older crowd was a great. Everyone around me had a flurry of wonderful reactions, and shed a few tears at the end. It was hard not to get swept up alongside them. And if the players on the stage consider themselves a family, then I think, even if it’s just for a brief moment, the audience must be as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Substance (2024) – All Eyes on Me</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/the-substance-2024-all-eyes-on-me/" />
    <updated>2024-10-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/the-substance-2024-all-eyes-on-me/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/b0itXhS69X33BvLi7uWjUZQs9MB.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Demi Moore getting more (eyes) than she bargained for&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last night was my fourth time seeing &lt;em&gt;The Substance.&lt;/em&gt; It was also my third time seeing it this month alone. That’s not surprising, as you can tell from an &lt;a href=&quot;https://unimelbfilmsoc.org/2024/09/19/the-substance-review/&quot;&gt;earlier review of mine&lt;/a&gt; that I’ve been obsessed since day one. Because Fargeat simply manages to pull off the impossible: creating a darkly funny and horrific satire that seems blunt on the surface, but provides a lot to chew on once you start peeling back all its fleshy layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s the motif of the colour yellow, representing both the fertility and rebirth found in egg yolk, as well as the destruction and toxicity of pesticides. There’s the overt homages to the Overlook Hotel from &lt;em&gt;The Shining,&lt;/em&gt; and Bernard Herrmann’s hauntingly obsessive &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; score ** mixed in at the end. While who can forget all the sadly ravaged food on display, which symbolises the ravenous hunger present in the entertainment industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, I won’t touch on any of that. Instead, I wish to provide some insight on the ways in which Fargeat explores, not just the Male Gaze, but all forms of perception. It’s clear from the very beginning that the film isn’t just talking about the way others see us, or the way society in general sees women, it also speaks to the way we see ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Minor plot elements may be spoiled for the sake of highlighting examples, but nothing here will ruin your experience if you haven’t seen the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The All-Seeing Eye&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/8dqZsevb5E8x29OFyr1neSp7bc9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;All stations tuned to Margaret Qualley&#39;s lips&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s get the most obvious example out of the way first: that ever-present male gaze. Whenever Elisabeth, or her alter ego, Sue record their respective shows, There is almost no studio audience. The crew are barely watching and when people do finally show up for the New Years Eve Show, they are shrouded in matte darkness. What takes their place are spotlights and camera lenses; these cold, oppressive and calculating cyclopses. Even Elisabeth’s next door neighbour is cocooned in the inhuman glass of a peephole when asking, what he believes to be Sue, on a date. I think it’s hard not to see these flashes of mechanical observers as anything other than a stand in for the Male Gaze. The camera will often take control in the more erotic shots of Sue. It will zoom in on her face as she puts a dripping Diet Coke can to her lips, it will rotate around her as it checks out her leathery motorcycle outfit, spinning her round like some rare Barbie doll on display, and it will magnify her arse to be gawked at by the rest of the crew. It’s understandable why a lot of people felt upset with the film, arguing that it was doing the exact objectification it set out to criticise. But that’s the beauty of the film’s over the top nature. By objectifying to such a comical degree, Fargeat is showing you the slight of hand that has been employed by both the entertainment and advertising industries for over a century now. Yes, most of us know it exists, so maybe some felt we didn’t need the primer to begin with, but as I’ll explain further on, I think Fargeat does a fantastic job in highlighting that women are subjected to these images just as much as men are. Men desire the body of the woman on screen, while a lot of women desire &lt;em&gt;to be&lt;/em&gt; that woman on screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;As Above, So Below&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/f5Yjq0CCfokPXuRQvlnlPq16tg0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Demi Moore unboxing her Substance haul!&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After witnessing a test of the titular substance on an egg yolk, we look down from on high as Elisabeth Sparkle’s star on the Hollywood Walk of Fame is built. We see it’s premiere, it’s degradation and its mistreatment. And throughout this montage, people come and go, their opinions of her changing with the passing seasons. And from our vantage point in the sky, having not even seen the woman yet, we already find ourselves judging her character. If the unfeeling camera lens was pure lust, the omniscient view we get from above, and sometimes below, becomes a form of judgement. Regardless of who is on screen, if we are either situated below or above them, we are judging them. It starts off small, we recoil when Elisabeth, now desperate to try the Substance, digs towards us through the trash to find the contact details she so carelessly threw away earlier. Or, we find ourselves looking down on Sue, who, laying on a ruffled silk bedspread, tries her best to grab our attention with an homage to &lt;em&gt;American Beauty,&lt;/em&gt; but as we’re not stationed looking up, like Kevin Spacey’s Lester, we’re simply not buying the performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, no group of shots more perfectly encapsulate this feeling of judgement than each of the shower scenes. Every time Sue and Elisabeth switch, there’s an accompanying shower scene. At first, we judge Sue from down low for enjoying her new younger body, and when Elisabeth wakes from her seven day coma for the first time, we judge, from our high ground, the horrific scaring on her spine stemming from a botched stitch job. But as Sue takes up more and more time for herself, and the longer we are stuck judging Elisabeth, we are, by extension, further distancing ourselves from her. By the time she’s reached her breaking point, curled foetal position on the shower floor, the camera raises itself to greater heights and the focal length shifts to create this sense of and endless drop. We feel sorry for Elisabeth, but by the end, it is only a passing pity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Self-Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/kvPcbG7tUDYv5sWcifzX7uidkun.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Demi Moore looking at the woman in the mirror&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If people are constantly judging our looks and actions, it’s hard not to have those same judgements stick with us. This, in the most unfortunate cases, reflects back onto us in the form of an internalised hatred for ourselves and distorts how we view our minds, and most obviously, our bodies. The mirror in Elizabeth’s bathroom becomes the focal point for: 1. moments of discovery (when she first wakes up as Sue), 2. moments of horror (when she looks at her deteriorating body after ‘a slight misuse’ of the Substance), and 3. moments of utter heartbreak (Demi Moore’s particularly poignant portrayal of Elisabeth’s breakdown before her date with the adorkable Fred). All these mirror scenes occur after either Sue or Elisabeth have a full day of hearing what other people have to say or think about them, or it’s after a severe malfunction with the Substance. Fargeat gives us these small pauses, allowing, or in some sense forcing, the audience to take a backseat. This time, the judgement doesn’t come from us, it comes from the characters themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, it’s not just Sue and Elisabeth’s seperate trips to the mirror that make up this portrait of hatred. As the film keeps having to remind both us and them, users of the Substance ‘are one’ and the same. Elisabeth is not viewing Sue’s blown up billboard as a jealous rival to beat, but witnessing the busty and distorted vision of her ideal self. It haunts her every step as she prepares to leave for her date with Fred, and when she stares at her older, more bulbous “reality” in the brass doorknob leading to her hallway, it ultimately destroys her. Meanwhile, Sue can’t bare to look at her old self, choosing to hide away Elisabeth’s larger than life headshot from view of the living room. That’s not to say the older star isn’t guilty of this herself, as she wears big bug eyed shades to avoid people’s gazes, simply so she doesn’t have to see herself reflected in their eyes. Vanity is a symptom of insecurity, which in itself is caused by the people who deem us worthwhile or worthless. Therefore, it’s no wonder Elisabeth and Sue avoid looking at each other – at themselves. Which is why it’s the ultimate irony for both of them that the audience see everything when they use the activator, as the audience can clearly see their contorted forms in the reflection of their pupils.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But seeing is believing, and as much as I like to yap about the movie I implore you to witness this masterpiece for yourselves, especially while you can still watch it in a crowded theatre. Because despite the serious subject matter and gross out moments, I think Fargeat just couldn’t help but make &lt;em&gt;The Substance&lt;/em&gt; a real feast for the eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It Came from the Archives – In a Violent Nature (2024)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/it-came-from-the-archives-in-a-violent-nature-2024/" />
    <updated>2024-10-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/it-came-from-the-archives-in-a-violent-nature-2024/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since today is the eve of All Hallow’s Eve, I thought what better way to celebrate it than by dusting off one of my old pieces; lost to time like some eldritch tome of curses. I’ve also chopped and changed a few things since I’ve a had a fair bit of time to reflect upon my experience. So, while it may not be fresh, hopefully this little morsel is spooky enough to send shivers – even a small tingle – down your spine. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scontent.fmel5-1.fna.fbcdn.net/v/t39.30808-6/485404350_1054799296683119_1823907239597806617_n.jpg?stp=cp6_dst-jpg_tt6&amp;amp;_nc_cat=103&amp;amp;ccb=1-7&amp;amp;_nc_sid=127cfc&amp;amp;_nc_ohc=EKUbd9z6XL4Q7kNvwGiSwco&amp;amp;_nc_oc=AdnpadlkXshfXav9ekECkEl4KaTDdBLN-tJyPuV2YFF5bQWl8VBG25WCfiuwV7Hh9ic&amp;amp;_nc_zt=23&amp;amp;_nc_ht=scontent.fmel5-1.fna&amp;amp;_nc_gid=5MvylzPtCSGk5TBGFyHmEw&amp;amp;oh=00_AfOrZMJQfJC-eSOslSrE3t6E_kO-f-ZxRDMMtEL0Npga4Q&amp;amp;oe=6866B57C&quot; alt=&quot;Vampire David Dastmalchian chilling with the killer himself&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above image was taken at The Overlook Film Festival and posted to Umbrella Entertainment’s socials on the 26th of July, 2024. In it, we see &lt;em&gt;Late Night with the Devil&lt;/em&gt; star, David Dastmalchian in a party store vampire costume, posed next to a menacing Jason Voorhees look alike in an old school smoke hood (a Vajen-Bader smoke helmet to be specific).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I did not know it yet, this was my first time meeting Johnny: the monster from Canadian filmmaker Chris Nash’s debut feature: &lt;em&gt;In a Violent Nature&lt;/em&gt;. I’d been invited to an advanced screening by a friend, and going off the title alone, I walked into a barren Crown cinemas on a particularly quiet Monday night knowing and expecting nothing. It wasn’t until a quarter of the way through the film, when Johnny uses a headless corpse to break a museum cabinet and pick up his signature mask, that I even realised this was the same creature I’d seen a few days before on Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a surprise twist for the genre, we are immediately thrust into the killer’s perspective. After a group of teens stumble upon an abandoned fire tower and unknowingly steal his mother’s locket, our protagonist, Johnny, drags himself up from the forest floor. Silently skulking through green wilderness and lakeside cabins, he hunts each member of the group one by one in increasingly tortuous ways until he can finally get what is rightfully his.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other difference from your usual horror fare is how quiet and distant everything feels as we embody Johnny. Nature foley replaces a traditional soundtrack, and we never stray too far away from his backside, the campers shot from a distance so that we never feel any closer to them. It’s only when Nash wants to showcase a bit of gory fun, and Johnny’s finished stalking his prey, that we get up all in those bloody details. This adds, for better or worse, a shockingly serene atmosphere to the whole production. It’s a form of minimalism that is by design – and budget constraints – calming. It forces you to connect with Johnny, creating an uneasy feeling when he finally commits horrendous acts of violence. However, by overindulging in this style of filmmaking (ninety percent of which is poorly edited walk cycles of an actor in a generic, tatty costume and cheap Halloween mask), &lt;em&gt;In a Violent Nature&lt;/em&gt; fails to successfully scare, or really unnerve at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, we can take a look at how the original &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th&lt;/em&gt; uses perspective to create a tense atmosphere. Similarly in the point of view of a killer, an unknown assailant lies in constant wait, stalking from a distance. Their deep and hissy breathing rattles the ears as they spy through cabin windows and across lakes at the local camp counsellors. The difference is, while we &lt;em&gt;see through their eyes&lt;/em&gt; , we (almost) never &lt;em&gt;see them.&lt;/em&gt; We don’t know this nameless killer, we hear stories from the counsellors of who they might be, but we’re never really sure until the very end. And we’re fearful because we’re in the killer&#39;s POV. We want to warn, scream or shout at the counsellors, but we can’t; the audience is powerless. An audience is always powerless, but here, watching &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th,&lt;/em&gt; they &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, it’s not always fair to compare contemporary works to the classics that inspired them, especially if they have a smaller team and less studio backing. So, let’s compare gore for gore and talk about the first &lt;em&gt;Terrifier&lt;/em&gt; film. Both are low-budget films, both are from directors whose past works were shorts for an anthology feature, and both are distributed here in Australia by Umbrella and streaming on Shudder. While both films match-up in the kill and gore department and have midpoint kills that shrink the privates and churn the stomach, only &lt;em&gt;Terrifier&lt;/em&gt; knows what to do with itself between kills. Art the Clown, and David Howard Thorton who plays him, are creepy, sadistic and menacing without even raising a finger. The clown mocks, stalks and plays with his prey; all with an exaggerated smile on his face. I didn’t care that the two main girls had stale dialogue and cardboard personalities, as soon as Art dragged his sack of tools into that burger shop, I was immediately tense. By contrast, Ryan Barret just doesn’t hold up as Johnny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After sitting with the film for a while, I realise Johnny is less a gleeful killer and more a bear that’s been poked by naive tourists, however, it’s clear from the kills that Nash wanted the film to be scary and not just a simple subversion like &lt;em&gt;Cabin in the Woods or Tucker &amp;amp; Dale vs. Evil.&lt;/em&gt; But by the film trying to have its cake and eat it too, it loses all sense of balance. Johnny kills too violently – and later on with a particularly unsettling kill, methodically – to be classified as a natural predator, and he doesn’t really embody an undead behemoth out for revenge. Instead, he feels more like an actor in prosthetics enjoying a casual walk through nature. It doesn’t help that without the mask, the natural lighting makes the costume look cheap. You can even see the seams of his disfigured face stand out in the harsh sunlight. If Nash had shortened the time between kills, had Barret embodied a similar stalking performance to the likes of Richard Brooker in &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th Part III&lt;/em&gt; or Kane Hodder in parts &lt;em&gt;VII&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; , or if the DOP had just gone for a first person angle like the original &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th, Violent Nature&lt;/em&gt; would, at the very least, be unsettling. And while the natural setting is a cool experiment in conventions and audience expectations, it’s Nash’s fear to commit to it completely that draws criticism from slasher die-hards like myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I would be remiss not to mention the one time when the whole ‘quiet and detached’ mood came together. In the third act, when final girl Kris escapes the forest with a branch piercing through her ankle, we finally lose sight of Johnny. Picked up by a local woman, we’re treated to a long monologue about a bear attack, but as the car careens down the road, much like Kris, we’re not paying attention to her allegory, we’re stressed about when Johnny’s going to come back for revenge. As Kris becomes faint from blood loss, her saviour stops the car to help bandage her up. Kris panics, imploring the woman to get back in the car and drive. Her eyes dart around. And as she stares into the wilderness, we soon find ourselves staring with her into a patch of forest, not quite sure if we can see something in the distance. It is at this moment where &lt;em&gt;In a Violent Nature&lt;/em&gt; finally understands what it needs to be successful. Nash, rightly, gets us used to seeing Johnny, used to knowing where he is, and used to hearing the thud of his boots and rattling of his hooks, only to take him away at the most pivotal moment. This is where the fear of &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; film is most potent. The supposedly ‘empty’ frame that we see through Kris’ eyes captures what the &lt;em&gt;Friday the 13th franchise&lt;/em&gt; mastered: a primal fear. If &lt;em&gt;In a Violent Nature&lt;/em&gt; spent &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; time in that fear, it could have been great. After all, there is no greater fear than the fear of the unknown; a fear that something sees us, but we don’t see them. And unfortunately, it seems like Nash was more concerned with making Johnny a pretty looking monster for social media, and as a result, horror fans see right through him.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Get Me Out of Here (2024)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/get-me-out-of-here-2024/" />
    <updated>2024-11-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/get-me-out-of-here-2024/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/Sw3mlJ5iIWSeSYjgiciKPymXw7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A 50th birthday party no-one wants to be a part of&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s difficult not to reminisce about a time when director Robert Zemeckis was at his peak. Especially when his latest project is so steeped in nostalgia as to make you sick. He’s always been a tech wiz, often leading teams of VFX artists, setting the standard for the next decade of filmmakers. Personally, I always return to the &lt;em&gt;Back to The Future Trilogy&lt;/em&gt; when I’m feeling down. Seeing Marty and Doc occupying the same temporal space as their past and future selves seems like a simple edit job now, but in the Eighties, it would have cost a pretty penny in reshoots, considering the one to two year gap between each sequel. But as boundary pushing as the visuals were for the time, that’s not what made the films so memorable. It was Zemeckis and Bob Gale’s screenplays – the ones with quirky yet deeply interesting characters, with both grand and hellish visions of the future and an earned sentimentality – that truly revolutionised what a time travel story could be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, skipping past Zemeckis’ extensive filmography, we arrive &lt;em&gt;Here:&lt;/em&gt; a quaint home in which all of human history exists at once. From the early native tribes of America to sixties swingers (one of whom is the inventor of the Lazy Boy), everyone seems to be intrinsically tied to this one magical spot. But what mainly carries us back and forward through the ages is the Young Family. Started by World War II veteran Al (Paul Bettany) and his wife Rose (Kelly Reilly), and carried on by their eldest son Richard (Tom Hanks) and his high school sweetheart, Vanessa (Robin Wright), the Youngs are a focal point onto which all other timelines latch. We pop in and out of Richard and Vanessa’s lives as they marry, have children, grieve the loss of loved ones, seperate and come back together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adapted from the graphic novel by Richard McGuire – whose depiction of one plot of land from a primordial stomping ground to a modern day family home spans 304 pages – it never seemed like an impossible idea to condense its essence to 104 minutes of film. Regardless, it was just improbable enough for Zemeckis to prove once again that he, and he alone, is at the forefront of innovative filmmaking. Actors are de-aged, aged up and morphed at breathtaking speeds, trees and plants are reconstructed and torn back down again, while eras are cut out of and into the house; a collage mending time and space into one complete moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this sounds incredible, but with an ideas man like Zemeckis, its all bound to fall apart somewhere along the pipeline. The most glaring issue is the look of the film, best described as a generative mess. You’d think a director neurotically obsessed with computer graphics would use some of &lt;em&gt;Here’s&lt;/em&gt; $50 million dollar budget to pay his VFX artists a decent wage. But its clear from the rubber foliage that spurts out of ground and the cartoonish wildlife that would have been laughed at even ten years ago, that Zemeckis would rather treat his A-List buddies to a fat pay check instead of actually making something appealing. And unsurprisingly, despite his team no doubt being aware of all the awful attempts at de-aging over the last few years, it’s the main selling point of the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the one static shot, characters can be filmed far enough away to save face. However, Zemeckis seems insistent on showing us Hank and Wright’s transformations up close and personal; as if he arrogantly believes his uncanny creations are any better than what we’ve seen before. Unreal Engine is making strides in the gaming sphere, with development teams working harder than ever to balance style with photorealistic faces. But for whatever reason, filmmakers seem hellbent on the engine earning its namesake, rotoscoping the living, and mostly the dead, onto these plastic cadavers that are supposed to immortalise their youth. Some would argue it’s moot to complain about &lt;em&gt;Here’s&lt;/em&gt; limitations. After all, it’s no Marvel budget. Nevertheless, the film is five times the size of an A24 indie and, I don’t know, maybe being Robert bloody Zemeckis gives you a bit more sway with the execs than your average director. It’s honestly baffling that he couldn’t even scrounge a little bit more cash for his production team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would argue the greatest eyesores in the film are these terrible morphing transitions that appear out of nowhere. We’re treated to several uninterrupted minutes of decent editing – a window into the next time period appears in a scene before completely cutting to it. A simple and effective tool for carrying us through time. But every now and then a cut would have these horrible interpolated splotches appear on screen. It’s jarring the first time it’s vomited up on screen, and only gets worse with each subsequent use. Slow motion scenes also have this awkwardness to them, in one moment, Wright runs towards the camera in a panic and looks like she’s walking through the scene, as if it were made of a thick cream. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/90847396/generative-ai-metaphysic-tom-hanks-robin-wright-zemeckis-here&quot;&gt;Zemeckis confirmed that he worked closely with Metaphysic to help produce deepfakes of the actors&lt;/a&gt;, so that facial capture could be streamlined. And to the surprise of no one, this is the same company who shamelessly revived Ian Holm in what amounted to nothing more than a cheap cameo in &lt;em&gt;Alien Romulus.&lt;/em&gt; But if using it saved Zemeckis the possibility of hiring actual VFX workers for capture, then what’s to stop him from using it to edit as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing wrong with wanting to push the boundaries of technology, but Zemeckis’ obsession has soured any goodwill the audience had for him, as while each production increases in scope, scale and innovation, the quality always decreases. This is largely due to the tech worlds own obsession on automation. So, naturally the more automated the process becomes for him, the less hands on Zemeckis is in the project. When the technology wasn’t there, like in &lt;em&gt;Who Framed Roger Rabbit?,&lt;/em&gt; he had to work harder to achieve the what he wanted, working closely with animators and nutting out the logistics of scene with Steven Spielberg for hours at a time. Now though, the 72 year old director is more than happy to sit back and let everyone else, man or machine, do the work for him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, the story has a similar energy, the screenplay coasting along a stream of generic hodgepodge that would have served better as a 30 minute short at Disneyland. Everything boils down to one of three things happening: A lazy observation about different eras repeating history (Influneza was just like COVID), References (Obvious Needle drops and the inventor of the Lazy Boy being a horndog), and people either wanting to be or not be here. The times we do stray away from the Young family – the Native Americans or a modern day African American family – are not only sparse but are quickly whisked away in favour of yet another joke about the white swingers having sex on an Lazy Boy prototype. Yet, even these attempts to be inclusive ring hollow after a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film acknowledges that Native Americans were the original inhabitants, but curiously doesn’t show any hint at colonisation. This suggest, whether implicitly or not, that the colonies just arrived their uncontested; a natural consequence of time moving forward. And while the modern family giving their son ‘the talk’ about police brutality is true to life, it felt empty and little whitewashed. These condescending appeals to a wider demographic outside a white sphere are only made more embarrassing when they service the Youngs. We watch a Native woman die, only for her remains to be dug up in the backyard, her necklace stolen and gawked at by the white people who live their now. Naturally, a family movie is never going to get violent nowadays, but it’s insulting to not at least acknowledge the darker side of history. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SeGeT3ZeKO0&quot;&gt;Broey Deschanel has a brilliant video essay about Forrest Gump&lt;/a&gt; and it’s appeal to conservative politicians. And seeing as nothing’s changed for Zemeckis, who may be liberal in his ideas, but whose habit of omitting history in favour of simplicity and sentimentality corrodes &lt;em&gt;Here&lt;/em&gt; into a empty form of nostalgia for any time but this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soulless, artless, and unfortunately, heartless, &lt;em&gt;Here&lt;/em&gt; is the embodiment of everything wrong with Zemeckis’ later career, and indeed, Hollywood at large.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Heretic (2024) – You May Not Like What You Find Down There...</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/heretic-2024-you-may-not-like-what-you-find-down-there/" />
    <updated>2024-11-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/heretic-2024-you-may-not-like-what-you-find-down-there/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/tmvbyMIv56hc03Mtgusj2koFWKj.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hugh Grant about to ABSOLUTELY DESTROY some mormon girls&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A24 has always taken a chance on weirder projects. Its almost part of their brand at this point to say yes where other production companies would say no. And while its had a pretty decent track record, its usually their horror films – &lt;em&gt;Hereditary, Talk to Me, I Saw the TV Glow&lt;/em&gt; – that have the greatest return on investment. So, it was easy to see why hype was building for &lt;em&gt;Heretic.&lt;/em&gt; A religious psychological horror with stunning cinematography by Park Chan-wook veteran, Chung Chung-hoon and a scenery chewing Hugh Grant attached as a villain; honestly who wouldn’t be excited?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was certainly keen. However, I had made the mistake of looking up the pair of filmmakers who were tasked with leading such a creative tour de force. Scott Beck and Bryan Woods are most known for writing the first &lt;em&gt;Quiet Place&lt;/em&gt; film for director John Krasinski. At the time, their screenplay was praised for prioritising sound in the big print (action lines) rather than visuals in order to communicate the film’s atmosphere and tension. Yet, they have fallen out of favour with audiences in the years since, as their solo directing efforts have led to either forgettable studio action movies like last year’s &lt;em&gt;65&lt;/em&gt; or lacklustre Blumhouse-esque horrors like &lt;em&gt;Haunt&lt;/em&gt; (2019).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the trailer was enough to suck me in, and I was even hopeful that with the support of an indie powerhouse like A24 behind them, Beck and Woods, finally free from the meddling of studio execs, would be able to pull off a miracle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, the film sets up just the right mood, as two young Mormon missionaries stare out at a mossy cliffside, chatting about condom sizes. Their conversation is just unserious enough to tell an audience what kind of girls they are; that while they’re pious, they’re immature enough to be swayed in their own beliefs. On the girls usual rounds of door to door pamphlet pushing, the more experienced Sister Barnes (Sophie Thatcher) offers to help the naive Sister Paxton (Chloe East) improve her conversion rate. But as the pair are either ignored by the adults around them or mocked by local youths – one even going as far as pantsing Sister Paxton in public – it seems today of all days will be less than successful. But hope is found in Mr. Reed (Hugh Grant), whose open interest in Mormon theology has already been documented by the church. So, as rain begins to buckle down and with nothing left to lose except a shameful walk back to the church, the exhausted Sisters ring his doorbell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/ou0IOkJKeCrFGd9most5RoHn60h.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hugh Grant smug in front of a candle&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reed is better than either of the girls could have hoped. He’s a polite older gentleman, whose gaiety couldn’t be more infectious. Yet, they give pause when he’s almost too eager to invite them in, as they cannot be alone with a man without another woman present in the home. Apologetic, Reed confirms that his wife is inside baking a delicious blueberry pie and encourages the girls to come in for something to eat. Once inside, Sister Barnes and Sister Paxton are calmed by the smell of pie wafting from the kitchen. And with Reed’s already extensive knowledge of the Book of Mormon – of which he already has a fully annotated copy stashed in his cupboard – Sister Paxton is guaranteed to have at least one success today. But it’s the little things that make Sister Barnes feel uneasy, the metal in the walls, the pointed questions from Reed about her family and past, and that despite their repeated insistence that his wife be present, he disappears into the back of the house, only to come back with more excuses. It’s only during one of these disappearances that everything clicks, as Sister Barnes notices a scented candle on the coffee table. Its scent: Blueberry Pie. With the front door locked by a ‘faulty’ mechanism, the Sisters decide to talk their way out of leaving before Mr. Reed catches on. But to their surprise, their ever so cordial host is more than happy for them to head home – they’ll just have to use the door at the back of the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heretic’s&lt;/em&gt; strength lies in the escalation of its mystery. Each new question poses greater ones. The film is eager for us to follow the girls down a rabbit hole of faith, existence and purpose without Reed ever keeping us in the loop. The house set is expertly built to be at once homely and unrecognisable. Corridors stretch and wind, stairs drop down into dank dungeons. Meanwhile library shelves stacked with texts and incandescent lights bathe rooms in a warm glow and feel. It’s decidedly English gothic in its setting, but American gothic in tone. The film has been heavily compared to &lt;em&gt;Barbarian&lt;/em&gt; (2022) ** online the way the camera and edit explore the house, and how each new room is a foreboding reveal all on its own. It’s an ever changing being that constantly keeps you guessing. But I would argue it alludes more closely to something like &lt;em&gt;Willy Wonka and the Chocolate Factory&lt;/em&gt; (1971), in which the increasingly expansive factory holds a test in each room, and only those children smart and kind enough to move forward will have access to the ‘true’ prize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of &lt;em&gt;Wonka,&lt;/em&gt; Hugh Grant’s Reed is devilishly sincere and the highlight of the entire film – a contrast to the Oompa Loompa role he notably despised. Reed is written well enough – even if his little factoids might be grating for some – but Grant’s gift of the gab and his ability to indulge in a small amount camp glues the whole character together. You expect his mask to slip into abject disgust at any moment, but he never does, and you realise he never had a mask to begin with. The scariest thing about Reed is the earnestness of his theological pursuits. He may deceive the girls to get them right where he wants: but he never hides his true self from them. Chung-hoon supports Reed with an uncomfortable closeness or a dutch angle here and there to really hone in on how creepy a simple smile or frown from Grant can be. Meanwhile, sound designer Chris Duesterdiek ratchets up Grant’s smallest mannerisms, turning his claps or the opening of his mouth into it’s own form of jump scare. Everything culminates into a wonderful setup for the frightful journey ahead. And while Reeds monologues are a delight to hear, it leaves the audience asking one question: where exactly are we going with all this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/as3Fo1b3o5zt09xI3y6Gx6aZ2Hz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hug grants smugness is too close for comfort&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without spoiling what it is exactly that Reed “found” in his extensive study, I fear his results will disappoint most audience members. Like his many monologues before, the ‘truth’ that the one true religion offers has same depth of thought as a r/Atheism post or a quick dive down the sophistry YouTube rabbit hole. Worst of all, the film almost seems to distance itself from any folk or cosmic horror, as if it’s too clever for something as juvenile as the supernatural. It felt like there was a balloon filling with all this great tension, but when it came time to popping it, someone had forgot to tie up the bottom, so it just sadly deflated out all that energy into hot, wet air. Woods and Beck, despite all their newfound freedom, still feel shackled to Studio Hell; clinging to the style that made their writing a success in the first place. Their insistence on PG-13 (M) horror that refuses to go farther than a few trickles of blood and limp body here and there is disappointing to say the least. And God forbid they try and push the religious angle a bit harder. As, by not ruffling to many pious feathers, Reed weakens as a villain. Even with all of Grant’s wonderfully realised acting, the resulting plot forces Reed to end on a painfully pitiful whimper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heretic,&lt;/em&gt; by having A24’s blessing, is able to pull out all the stops to create a great horror premise. But unfortunately, I don’t think Beck and Woods really knew what to do with themselves, much less were ready for something this complex. Nevertheless, I would watch it all again, just to spend two more hours watching Hugh Grant having the time of his life.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The People&#39;s Joker (2022) and the Satirical Power of Being Sincere.</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/the-peoples-joker-2022-and-the-satirical-power-of-being-sincere/" />
    <updated>2024-11-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/the-peoples-joker-2022-and-the-satirical-power-of-being-sincere/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/eDnKYIjTtsU6iL4eZ0e1l68HUTM.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vera Drew going full Joker&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To call &lt;em&gt;The People’s Joker (2022)&lt;/em&gt; a parody would be doing both the film, and Vera Drew herself a disservice. Neither would it be fair to call it a “fan film”, as Vera might be passionate about DC Comics and its cinematic universe, but she also has extensive credits as a comedian and filmmaker in her own right. Having edited both &lt;em&gt;An evening with Tim Heidecker&lt;/em&gt; (2020) and Sacha Baron Cohen’s &lt;em&gt;Who Is America? (2018),&lt;/em&gt; she has the chops necessary to pull off such a brazen project. Naturally inspired by adult swim shows like &lt;em&gt;Tim and Eric Awesome Show, Great Job (2007),&lt;/em&gt; it’s no wonder the film is more than just a chronically online shitpost. Despite what the heavy use of green screen might have you believe, the film put its money where its mouth is. Lovingly gaudy 3D models replace real actors and professional animators splice in their work to connect scenes together. The Riddler’s scenes were filmed through a Zoom call and it works seamlessly because Vera has set up such a ridiculous world. These “amateurish” touches are intentionally crafted for laughs and could only be cohesively brought together by a master editors. This “cheapness” allows us as an audience to be lulled into a false sense of security. Because there’s no way the silly clown movie could have something heartfelt to say, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vera herself plays Joker the Harlequin, as she recounts her rise from a repressed stand up comic in Gotham to the trans villainess we all know and love. Starting out life as a boy in the wrong body, “Drew” is taken by their mother to Arkham Asylum in the hopes of curing her son’s perpetual sadness. Dr. Crane prescribes Joker with Smylex, a gas that induces a manic level of happiness in the user. Joker lives out most of her adolescence as “Drew”, gassing herself silly whenever something is likely to make her upset, angry or any other emotion not deemed “happy” enough. That is until UCB, Gotham’s clown stand-in for SNL, complete with a janky Lorne Michaels, is looking for fresh young talent to head their new lineup. Having watched the show as a kid, Joker heads to Gotham ready to make her comedy debut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it soon becomes apparent from the invasive audition procedures of scanning genitalia and expensive tuition fees that the school is limiting Joker’s comedic potential. That, and she can’t tell a good joke to save her life. So when fellow student, Penguin eggs her on to create her own school of anti-comedy, the pair create a stand up venue for all of UCB’s outcasts. Although Joker still struggles to get any of her material off the ground, she finds comedy gold in using Smylex to laugh at her fellow comics most tragic backstories. In finding her niche, Joker is finally able to shed her “Drew” persona and become the woman she was always meant to be: Joker the Harlequin. But as her own comedy career takes off, their is one caped crusader who still stands in her way: Batsy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film refuses to shy away from any of its pop culture references. Joker dates a Mr. J (Kane Distler), taking a page from Jared Leto’s turn as the Crown prince of Crime. He’s as “damaged” as his head tattoo would have you believe, being as crazed, narcissistic and downright abusive as the real deal (Joker or Leto? Same difference, really). His non villain name is even a nod to Jason Todd, who both in the comics and animated movies, adopts the Joker’s old alias, the Red Hood, becoming a sometimes enemy to Batman. Meanwhile, Ra’s Al Ghul, Joker’s mentor and idol at UCB straight up borrows lines from &lt;em&gt;Batman Begins (2005)&lt;/em&gt; , their training montage even having backgrounds ripped straight from the film, or fight scenes rotoscopped in the case of the animated segments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, it’s what the film does with these references that is truly magical. Vera, for all her magnificence as a film editor and shit-poster, is also an equally proficient screenwriter, taking all these tropes, references and funny gags about current politics and turning it into a meaningful story about a trans woman coming of an age. A woman living in a society that actively despises her and desiring a profession whose most high profile entertainers actively mock her existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Crane for example, he could have been just a small reference to Scarecrow and nothing more. But while his fear toxin is replaced with Smylex, Vera uses him as a metaphor for the internalised fear of trans bodies and minds, Smylex naturally being the “cure” to suppress trans identity, replacing it with a blank happiness. UCB may be a over the top parody of SNL, but it also hides within itself criticisms of the comedy industry at large; big institutions, whose convoluted audition processes and favourable bias towards those already in the industry, gate keep disenfranchised creatives from a successful career, incentivising them to prove their “diversity” to a board of white execs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vera’s comedy is not a shield from criticism, rather a slingshot from which she can take aim at the people in power. and that doesn’t just include people in the comedy and film industry, but those currently threatening the lives of trans children everywhere: concerned parents. Starting off as a hyperbolic caricature of a single mother (with impeccable comedic timing from Lynn Downey), Joker’s Mum is a neurotic hypochondriac, scared of her son moving an inch, let alone questioning their gender identity. But as Joker embraces more of herself, Downey’s performance gives way to a sincerity and level of sadness that’s uncomfortable to watch. Even the smallest word between the mother and daughter becomes a knife to the gut. Not many comedy films can leave you feeling choked up but Vera, knows to put earnest moments where you least expect them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The People’s Joker&lt;/em&gt; is a hidden gem that speaks to what a post Marvel and DC superhero film could be. It may have started life as a parody, but the care and thought put into the project, as well as Vera’s willingness to flesh out characters that DC have spent the better half of a decade either ignoring or rehashing previous film iterations instead of something new, it’s understandable why people are going Gaga for this crowdfunded indie darling.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Godzilla, King of the Monsters! (1956)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/godzilla-king-of-the-monsters-1956/" />
    <updated>2024-11-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/godzilla-king-of-the-monsters-1956/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/v4Udc9IcrdhdFaTKliUXkNTG86v.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Raymond Barry looking just as scared as you are to watch this film.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About a week ago I saw the first &lt;em&gt;Godzilla&lt;/em&gt; from 1954. I was playing catch-up, having missed both the Astor Marathon at MIFF and ACMI’s GodzillaFest, and although I wasn’t able to see it with an audience, thanks to a Cinema Nova screening, I still got to see my big boy on the big screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite its age, Ishiro Honda’s classic could hardly be called dated. It builds tension by putting us in a state of not knowing alongside our main characters. Sailor’s are mysteriously consumed by a white light before their ships sink to the bottom of the ocean. Or a family shudder inside their home, frightened by the screams from their youngest son outside, only for the house to collapse on top of them. It’s a far grimmer creature feature than you’d think, simply because it shows you the fear of the people suffering rather than the monster itself. Information is trickled out in such a way as to make Godzilla almost Lovecraftian in nature. But his radioactive footprints and fire breath seem to suggest another story entirely. An unnatural mutation has occurred, exposing Godzilla to atom bomb testing has made him a monster of horrifying proportions. He is man’s undoing, but also, his creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Godzilla may ultimately be a man in a rubber suit, but Honda was skilful enough to use lighting tricks to his advantage. What is shown of the monster is either obscured by mountains, submerged in water or cast in the long shadows of the night. Even before he’s made an appearance, stormy skies become his substitute; giving him the air of Nature’s vengeful avatar. In an age where its fellow features, and even some of its sequels, have aged like milk on modern screens, the original is able to salvage most of its horror by simply embracing the dark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, being so enthralled with the first entry, and seeing as their was still time to celebrate his 70th, I decided to seek out more of Godzilla’s offerings. The immediate follow-up &lt;em&gt;Godzilla Raids Again (1955)&lt;/em&gt; did bring us the concept of Kaiju battles with its introduction of Angurius, but Motoyoshi Oda’s upbeat action and day lit scenes are a far cry from Honda’s original vision of horror.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I want to write about today is &lt;em&gt;Godzilla, King of the Monsters!&lt;/em&gt; A story that had me truly baffled, as evening reading the discourse around the film brought up more questions than answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Localisation or Bastardisation?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/iog18AUHDUFL8Ra7wje7ibaiMg2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Raymond Burr and Frank Iwanaga staring non-chalantly at the carnage&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film shows up as the third entry in the Criterion Channel’s playlist for the Shōwa era&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/godzilla-king-of-the-monsters-1956/#fn1&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of Godzilla films, although it’s not listed in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Godzilla*(franchise)#Filmography&quot;&gt;Wikipedia’s official filmography for the franchise.&lt;/a&gt; That’s because it’s not a new film, but an American re-release of the original. So, imagine my surprise when going in blind, I was treated to a fully English voiceover introducing American correspondent, Steve Martin (Raymond Burr), as he clambers out of the scorched remains of Tokyo from the first film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Used to seeing flashbacks of &lt;em&gt;Godzilla&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Raids Again&lt;/em&gt; , and seeing Honda’s name as co-director alongside Terry O. Morse, I thought Honda might be trying to reach western audiences, seeing as its references to atomic bomb testing and the use of one threat to destroy another was clearly a warning to those outside of Japan. Excited to see what new perspective he was about to give us, I didn’t mind that it re-established the scene at the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when the bandaged Martin spoke to a barely disguised double of Emiko, I knew immediately what this was. &lt;em&gt;King of the Monsters!&lt;/em&gt; is a localised version of the original, which abridges a lot of the source material in favour of having to forgo any subtitling (which did exist, but was hard to implement at the time). Yet, &lt;em&gt;King of the Monsters!&lt;/em&gt; is less a faithful Dub and more a complete rework – that is, if the only “work” they focused on was bringing in the demolition crew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inconsistent dubbing is the most glaring issue, with the important actors dubbed in scenes, only for flashbacks to those same scenes, like in Dr. Serizawa’s lab, inextricably having the original Japanese dialogue. While larger scenes, like the discussion in parliament, are either summarised in voiceover by Martin, or translated directly to him by security officer Tomo Iwanaga (Frank Iwanaga), who acts as his interpreter throughout the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every one of Burr’s added scenes sticks out like a sore thumb, cheaply made sets and flat lighting, no doubt due to the budget constraints of American TV, clash hard with Honda’s original vision: a dark and sombre Japan. And while the dubbing is a necessary evil, the voice actors don’t remotely try to match the original performances. Their line reads are often dry and hastily delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, what remains of Honda’s work still look incredible, even if its often undercut by Burr’s presence. That same scene where a boy watches his family get crushed under the weight of their house is as harrowing as ever. It’s just a shame that it’s immediately followed up by Martin and Iwanaga starring blankly onwards, wet from the storm as they fight off a light breeze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version was no doubt disappointing for most audiences. Or, at least it would have been, if most of them knew about the original. But unless you were still in primary school like I was, most film fans would know that this version of Godzilla was the only English version released until the 50th anniversary edition in 2004. Most were unaware that Honda’s original cut even existed&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/godzilla-king-of-the-monsters-1956/#fn2&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. And as Raymond Burr’s name headlines the credits in big bold letters, supercedeing the original actors – including &lt;em&gt;Seven Samurai’s&lt;/em&gt; Takashi Shimura – you can’t help but feel skeptical about the whole production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is streamlined. Important contextual details are entirely absent. An explanation for Dr. Serizawa’s eye, of which he lost in the war, is entirely absent. H-Bomb testing is mentioned, but any criticisms of America and its actions over Nagasaki have been entirely stripped away. Meanwhile, the final moral debate between Ogata and Dr. Serizawa is boiled down to “responsibility” and “reality” versus “fear” before being quickly forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Criterion DVD commentary, &lt;em&gt;Godzilla&lt;/em&gt; historian David Kalat agrees that the removal of textual elements lessens the film’s effect, but defuses the idea that their is any intentional foul play from the filmmakers. He argues that the “subtext” remains and critics at the time still understood the film’s stance on nuclear weapons. However, while it may be true that editing for TV required the removal of scenes “[which] didn’t involve the main cast and weren’t essential for following the plot”, considering the scene mentioned before, in which two main characters are present, it becomes clear that certain liberties were taken for a less critical and clean cut ending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s even harder to stomach about the film is that Ishiro Honda himself was not made aware of any of the changes made to film. And being a young filmmaker, was just excited that Hollywood, known for the monster movies that inspired the film, were interested in buying the distribution rights. It wasn’t until &lt;em&gt;King of Monsters!&lt;/em&gt; was redistributed as a Japanese dub a year later that he finally got to see what they had done to it. While his comments about the film remained generally positive, it seems insulting to attach Honda’s name to a project that, by all accounts removed a majority of his work – not to mention marketing it as a brand new American film shot on location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole film feels scummy at best, and downright manipulative at worst. And that’s no doubt in part due to Joseph E. Levine. Known for his experience in advertising and being the main producer behind a sea of exploitation films, Levine bought &lt;em&gt;Godzilla&lt;/em&gt; for distribution in America for relatively cheap, no doubt banking on Japan’s postwar economic struggles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Though Japan’s economy began to revive in the early 1950s, the poverty and devastation of the postwar years were still recent memories. Personal incomes remained very low, and the country suffered massive trade deficits; therefore, $25,000 in highly coveted American currency was indeed a huge deal. But while the money was a boon to Toho, the amount was an absolute steal for…American distributors, a tiny fraction of the bargain price that Warners had paid for The Beast from 20,000 Fathoms.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Steve Ryfle and Ed Godziszewski&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s doubtful that O. Morse had the same intentions as his producers, as Kalat also mentions on the commentary, &lt;em&gt;Unknown World (1951)&lt;/em&gt; – the director’s previous work was staunchly anti-nuclear. However, it’s the subtle changes to &lt;em&gt;Godzilla’s&lt;/em&gt; script, like the removal of Dr. Serizawa describing how he would be tortured for information on the Oxygen Destroyer if the government couldn’t get ahold of his notes, that maybe point to an implicit bias as an American. And while Kalat ultimately dismisses viewing the the original &lt;em&gt;Godzilla&lt;/em&gt; through an “anti-american” lens – albeit one he “stands behind” – there’s no denying the language and behaviour of main cast is fundamentally different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Godzilla, King of the Monsters!&lt;/em&gt; might be a fun look at film history, but it also speaks to the more horrendous habits of the industry. It reminds us once again of the importance of media preservation, as what’s ‘original’ is always going to be what’s ‘available’. We may not have as many problems with translations anymore – considering the internet has given rise to fan localisations. Yet, considering Netflix’s awful decision to default to their shameful dub of &lt;em&gt;Squid Game&lt;/em&gt; on its release or James Cameron’s AI upscaled 4K “restoration” being the only way to watch &lt;em&gt;Judgement Day&lt;/em&gt; without having a copy of the Lionsgate Bluray, it’s clear even a director’s blessing won’t save their film from being torn to shreds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;footnotes-sep&quot;&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Japan denotes eras with the corresponding emperor’s and the length of their reign. The films from (1954-1975) were therefore made while Emperor Shōwa was still in power. &lt;a href=&quot;https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/godzilla-king-of-the-monsters-1956/#fnref1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ishiro Honda: A Life in Film, from Godzilla to Kurosawa,&lt;/em&gt; Steve Ryfle and Ed Godziszewski, pg. 105-106 &lt;a href=&quot;https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/godzilla-king-of-the-monsters-1956/#fnref2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Babygirl (2024) and Life on Autopilot</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/babygirl-2024-and-life-on-autopilot/" />
    <updated>2025-01-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/babygirl-2024-and-life-on-autopilot/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/9U4OtxswdzKRcYKyR3W1KnLi6hN.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nicole Kidman disassociating in a theatre&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Romy (Nicole Kidman) is the top dog at Amazon-esque e-commerce site striving to lead the charge in automated workflows. As packing bots flow up and down on a rail system, we’re told how important it is for their packing drones to have the same “accountability” as their human workers, and to bring a level of humanity back into the delivery room. Yet you could argue that the SHE-E-O’s home life is anything but human. She barely raises a fuss when her daughters act out, answering emails while barely present at the breakfast table, and ‘performs’ in bed for her dramaturg husband, Jacob (Antonio Banderas) before rushing off to really climax to fetish porn – muffling her real desires with a wet hand. Romy – like her company drones – experiences life on-rails, and despite her position of power, doesn’t really know how or when to get off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when an untrained dog goes berserk outside her building, setting its sights on her, she seems to face her fate the same way she always does: with a tired and limp acceptance. Except the booming voice of a stranger calls the dog back and Romy locks eyes not with the owner of the animal, an anxious and timid bystander, but the young man who just saved her life. As Samuel (Harris Dickinson) crouches down, offering a treat from his palm and stroking the scruff of dog’s neck, he stares Romy down; looking right into the depths of her flawed soul and saying with eyes alone, ‘you’re welcome.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bedevilled spark ignites in Romy after this ordeal, an awkward yearning that only complicates further when Samuel shows up as part of the internship program at the company. Samuel doesn’t shy away from her either, sliding in invasive questions and inappropriate banter, mocking her leadership skills and placing himself exactly where he’s not wanted. But unlike the other arseholes around the office, he may hide behind the guise of a naive intern, but he doesn’t hide his desires from her, and she him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when their play-fighting culminates in a mentorship turned erotic affair between the two of them, it’s up to pair of them to decide the ground rules. That is, if they can figure out who should be in charge of their little situationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/kwQ9hJi11R2bzHF5LpcBecHX2cI.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nicole Kidman and Harris Dickinson in a sensual brace&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modelled after the erotic thrillers of Paul Verhoeven ( &lt;em&gt;Basic Instinct, 1992)&lt;/em&gt; and Adrian Lynne ( &lt;em&gt;Fatal Attraction, 1987)&lt;/em&gt; , it seems, at first, unfathomable why Kidman’s character would go for a softie like Dickinson when she lays next to suave icon Banderas every night, who himself played a problematic (or in his case, psychotic) bad boy in Pedro Almodovar’s &lt;em&gt;Tie Me Up! Tie Me Down! (1989).&lt;/em&gt; But Dickinson somehow gaslights, gatekeeps and (boy)girl bosses his way into the hearts of the audience. In one sense sure of himself, in another incredibly nervous, his performance is a sleight of hand trick that impresses both us and the investors. Not unfamiliar with keeping her &lt;em&gt;Eyes Wide Shut&lt;/em&gt; and letting out her inner freak, Kidman is more than willing to scrape hands and knees if it means going toe to toe with her onscreen boy toy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, for all its bravado and hyper-sexual wantonness, &lt;em&gt;Babygirl&lt;/em&gt; is surprisingly more sensitive than its predecessors. Boundaries may be crossed, characters – like Romy’s PA, Esme (understated yet brutally played by fellow Australian Sophie Wilde) – may blackmail their way into the Dragon’s Den, and families may be destroyed, but the film never loses its underlying tenderness. That’s partly due to Samuel’s nature as a character. In &lt;em&gt;Fatal Attraction, Basic Instinct&lt;/em&gt; and even international endeavour’s like Japanese horror film, &lt;em&gt;Audition (1999)&lt;/em&gt; , Alex, Cathrine and Asami respectively are psychotic conduit’s for a more existential power; deities of karmic destruction against the men (or a masochistic Michael Douglas), who sleep around, give into their carnal urges and break the rules to regain some of their past youth and glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for Romy, who despite having a position of power in a ‘progressive’ company must, taboo or no, repress her sexuality out of shame, Samuel offers a firm but kind hand in her awakening. “You know what people want and desire.” she says to Samuel after one of their nights out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every scene of Romy crawling on her knees, Samuel will hold her, not caress her or kiss her, but just hold her in his arms. He’ll find her in a nightclub and guide her safely out of the mosh pit, he doesn’t just see through her, he sees &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; her. Jacob may show her love, but he has barely any time to look away from his rehearsal, much less have time to look at her. Even when he sleeps with Romy, their sex, whether he knows it or not, is done for his benefit. So, when Samuel finally does something for Romy, finally sees her for who she is, she can’t help but see him too. “I scare myself sometimes.” he says to Romy. But she already knows. She tells him that his deep care for others outweighs his nastier sexual impulses just as her tenacity outweighs her passivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Babygirl,&lt;/em&gt; it seems then shares more in common with the likes of &lt;em&gt;Secretary (2002),&lt;/em&gt; a more erotic than thrilling romance that sees Maggie Gyllenhaal’s Lee channel her self-harm into something more ‘healthy’, working under a spineless lawyer with a sadism fetish. In both films, what starts off as a problematic distraction from their empty lives, soon produces a sense of purpose for both members in the relationship. For Romy and Lee, Samuel and Grey (unrelated to the Christian Grey of E.L James’ series) become conduits of their inner strength, and surprisingly, their independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/fLxFRSQ4iOBjt1W3IThZzp6Cmb9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Harris Dickinson looking at you from across the club&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film does try to get around the murkiness of the situation – the age-gap, the intern/CEO power dynamic and the corporate corruption – by making both parties just as conflicted and confused as the audience is. When the role-play leaks out into their real lives, neither Samuel or Romy are sure who started it, who’s in control or who’s been manipulating whom. At the very least it’s done with more tact than either &lt;em&gt;Instinct&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Attraction,&lt;/em&gt; who paint Michael Douglas as a hapless sap who just so happened to hook-up with a cold and calculating psycho bitch. However, when the film implies ending a career with “one phone call” is equally harmful to asking your young intern to do sexual favours for you or you’ll “take care of him,” the writing hits little snags that don’t exactly scream solidarity with the victims of abuse or workplace harassment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, director Halina Reijn brings back her kinetic and on the pulse filmmaking from &lt;em&gt;Bodies, Bodies, Bodies&lt;/em&gt; and gives the erotic thriller a much needed facelift after dire drought of the 2010’s and their (seemingly) &lt;strong&gt;50 Years of Gray&lt;/strong&gt; studio slop. Supported with a breathy and climactic soundtrack by Cristobal Tapia De Veer, Reijin brings a freak energy that only Luca Guadagnino &lt;em&gt;(Challengers, Queer)&lt;/em&gt; can currently match. A highlight is back at the nightclub when Romy is looking for Samuel. The audience is treated to a gorgeously rendered, if epilepsy inducing, club experience. Overwhelming and definitely overstimulating, it captures the horrors and beauty of nightlife in one fell swoop – all without ever feeling watered down. So when Samuel and Romy finally grasp for each other in that sea of people, Romy, instead of feeling swallowed up, feels protected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Babygirl&lt;/em&gt; may be a much softer take on the erotic thriller, but that makes its hard edges stick out a whole lot more. It may be inconsiderate at times – largely due to the nature of its genre trappings – but Reijn is undoubtedly more equipped to try and unpack such a complex relationship than her male predecessors ever were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, it not’s the dolled up fake organisms – the fake nice family men – but the guttural, authentic and primal orgasm, the stone cold bitches, who turn the most heads.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What&#39;s the Rush? – Peter Weir and Sitting in the Moment.</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/whats-the-rush-peter-weir-and-sitting-in-the-moment/" />
    <updated>2025-02-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/whats-the-rush-peter-weir-and-sitting-in-the-moment/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/h1BOZ76ITbZtXlQ6sndaek8rQjg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The boys of Dead Poets Society hanging out in their cave&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Weir has always been a rather strange director in the Australian canon. He’s a household name, but no one’s quite sure what for? He’s the type of artist whose filmography elicits surprised utterances of, “He made that!?” or “The Cars That Ate what?” But that’s arguably what makes him a talented director, his ability to blend his essence into seemingly anything. At first, you might wonder what an Australian is doing making a film about an American Prep School, yet look a little closer in Dead Poets Society (1989), and you’ll see the Australian Private School experience, complete with Chapel, enigmatic English Teachers, and bagpipes wheezing “Scotland the Brave” every hour on the hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter how far he strays from our little isolated continent, he always finds a way to take a little piece of home with him on the journey. But what’s that little spark that permeates all of his films? What makes a Weir film a Weir film?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing &lt;em&gt;Dead Poets&lt;/em&gt; with Finn, (a friend who happens to share the same name, and not me excusing going to the movies alone) at ACMI, I couldn’t help but comment on how disjointed every one of Weir’s films felt. He has that eye that all great Aussie directors have (Samuel sitting in that field of flowers at the end of &lt;em&gt;Witness&lt;/em&gt; (1985) comes to mind) but has that same penchant for meandering in a fairly decent premise, that to most writers, seems rather wasteful. Finn argued that sitting with his characters, like when we hang out in the cave with the boys of Welton Academy as they idly chat, allows us as audiences members to develop a greater investment in the boys when things eventually start moving along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/41Mlaj6wfjlF4wQaVH0tjfDXvMi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The girls chilling at Hanging Rock&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sense, as another filmmaker might cut away far too quickly for the sake of plot, leaving us wondering if we even knew any of these boys at all. Weir’s storytelling may not be his strong suit, but my God does he have a unique. Everyone of his films carries this much darker undercurrent. That accent of Australian Gothic in &lt;em&gt;Picnic at Hanging Rock&lt;/em&gt; (1975) – warbling analogue synths, oppressive yet heavenly camerawork, and actors seemingly possessed by some otherworldly force – can be found everywhere in his work. Neil’s late night foray as Puck in &lt;em&gt;Dead Poets&lt;/em&gt; will forever be seared into my memory, and the people of Paris and their obsession with road “accidents” were comically frightful. It’s why I can never come away hating one of his films, their is always an image to latch onto, a painting which inspires in me an almost religious fervour that’s difficult to stifle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/bRRxELS8dK3cpqFhaTQcIENAPOI.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Truman finding the sun in the palm of his hand&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why &lt;em&gt;The Truman Show&lt;/em&gt; (1998) is, in my opinion, not only his best film, but the culmination of his greatest qualities as a director. Jim Carrey’s Truman is watched around the clock. Were constantly made aware of the edges of a camera lens as we follow him around the manmade town of Seahaven. We sit behind the newsagent’s desk as he gets the morning paper, we observe him through his car’s steering wheel as he listens to the radio. When Truman snaps, its understandable, but when he begins to hold his supposed wife Meryl hostage, he’s filmed like a psychotic spouse ready to kill. First person shots, dutch angles and hysterics, we see a broken and dangerous man. But what’s far more horrifying is how dismissive director Christof and the rest of the crew are to Truman’s wellbeing, thinking nothing of the time they traumatised him by “killing” his father during a boating accident so that he would not only blame himself, but fear travelling by sea to try and escape the studio. The premise of a round the clock live TV Show suits Weirs ability to sit in a scene, as Truman’s daily routine is filled with seemingly innocuous activities. But thanks to Screenwriter Andrew Niccol, whose world building is always fleshed out, if a little blunt on themes. There’s now an underlying pace to everything. Niccol creates the little hiccups in The Truman Show’s production that start to unravel Truman’s mind. Meanwhile, Weir uses his experience as a director to inform the central theme: a controlling relationship between a creator and his creation only leads to disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/yrVtvlL4X3YrBF2VWMh5jN55XCS.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Truman giving one last bow before heading out into the unknown&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Weir is not a storyteller but a painter. A man concerned more with Film as a form of enlightenment for others than a means of personal catharsis for himself. And while his plots aren’t always the most exciting, his portraits of people and places are wonderfully detailed. His works may not be remembered as solely his, but his art speaks to future filmmakers and creators. Like the spectres of dead poets, each one reaches out to all the artists inside of us and says simply this: “Seize the day!”&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Se7en (1995) – Wading Through Apathy</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/se7en-1995-wading-through-apathy/" />
    <updated>2025-02-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/se7en-1995-wading-through-apathy/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/dYjZ27hDw2QFaEIfzbNGwW0IkV9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brad Pitt and Morgan Freeman coming to terms with their &#39;killer&#39; ending&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Se7en&lt;/em&gt; was one of those Fincher Films I hadn’t seen until sometime last year. Mostly due to the fact that, like most YouTube addicted kids in the mid 2010’s, I’d absorbed the plot – as well as the infamous twist – through countless top ten videos. Mills has his Cliff Notes for &lt;em&gt;Dante’s Inferno,&lt;/em&gt; while I have my WatchMojo Top Tens for &lt;em&gt;Fight Club&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Se7en.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, knowing everything going in did taint my first watch, as I found it frustrating that, for a detective film, the brash David Mills and older, wiser Somerset were always offended by each other even when they earnestly started to work together. On the surface, they seemed to show little to no growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything else about the film was wonderful: The forever rainy city, the gruesome crime scenes and disgraced actor Kevin Spacey’s unsettling performance were all top tier. Yet, the pain point of the film’s central relationship was forever in the back of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, naturally I was a bit hesitant to see it at the Astor last Thursday, but it felt silly to miss out on a thirty year anniversary screening – especially with the promise of a 35mm print.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it should surprise no one that having sat with the film for almost a year, and seeing it up on the big screen, something finally clicked up their in the front row balcony. The only thing feeling silly by the end of the film was me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot has the usual hard boiled trappings of a detective noir: Somerset is on the verge of retiring from the homicide unit when he uncovers a series of murders connected to the Seven Deadly Sins. Hardened enough to know when to quit, he refuses the case, but when his younger partner, the out-of-town Detective Mills, gets assigned it instead, he decides to work alongside him in an effort to protect the young man from the horrors this case has in store for him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, what’s special about &lt;em&gt;Se7en&lt;/em&gt; is Fincher’s use of the commonplace setting: the unforgiving, seeing it as a tool. He explores how our characters might go about communicating in a world that has taught them to remain distant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somerset is hated by his colleagues and put up with by friends for always caring about what happens after a case. What will happen to the orphan of murdered parents? Who are these people we’re looking at like bags of meat, what are their names, what did they do? Years of this has finally worn him down. His retirement is a means of escape, a refuge from “a place that embraces and nurtures apathy as if it were a virtue.” He’s stopped trying to help a city that keeps refusing to be saved; and if saving himself is the consolation prize, so be it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But something changes when Mills enters the picture. He may be an experienced homicide detective for someone so young, but his rural cases are nothing compared to ravenous creeps of the big city. Somerset, faced with the possibility that Mills might be chewed up and spit back out as a carbon copy of himself, feels the need to help his partner. A paternal instinct kicks in for the old man: if he can’t save the city, he’ll at least save his partner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/ejcYNEKc0C59dqNBH9CtJ0WXNd1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brad Pitt and Morgan Freeman bonding over evidence&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But like most father’s, Somerset has a hard time showing his appreciation for Mills. “It’s easier to beat a child than it is to raise it.” he says to Mills over drinks. And while Somerset doesn’t accost Mills, he certainly berates and belittles him for having a short-temper and being a bit too eager to cause a fuss. But, eventually some of his old kindness shines through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The library scene, which I once derided for making Mills’ involvement in the case fairly minimal, is powerful in it’s subtlety. Somerset uses small gestures, like his envelope of research for Mills or his insistence to hear the testimony of the nightclub hostage while sticking Mills with interrogating the owner, as a form of showing love or appreciation for his young partner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, Mills’ own constant chatter at crime scenes and his desperation to be a part of the investigations is his confused and often crude way of getting Somerset to open up more. The constant arguing, that feels like stagnant character development on a first watch, is Fincher’s way of showcasing the love languages of two people immersed in a city that has forgotten how to love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Doe meanwhile, is the killer that represents everything wrong with the city. If Somerset’s apathy makes him want to run away from problem and Mill’s makes him want to fight to clean it up, regardless of what people think, John’s apathy makes him want to destroy it. John sees sin in every man, woman and child. He will throw up on a man who speaks about the weather, only to laugh at his annoyance. His role as religious disciple is fitting, as he conduct his “work” with the same dispassionate judgement his creator passes onto him and all the other creatures who exist within the city walls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once Somerset and Mills pick up pieces of the puzzle left by John, the serial killer gains a vested interest in the pair for entirely different reasons. He finds Somerset equal in intellect, but his already defeated attitude inspires none of his sadistic tendencies. However, Mills is yet to be broken. Their is a hopeful spirit left in him yet to humble. So, his “surprise” is not shocking for it’s grotesqueness, it’s shocking because it was planned, right down to the second, despite knowing nothing of other people’s feelings, John knows exactly what buttons to push.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why do I still feel hopeful after the ending of &lt;em&gt;Se7en&lt;/em&gt;? Why does it make me hopeful for our own future despite the horrors that lie ahead? Because while, someone like Mills may break, his ideals live on in the reformed Somerset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You think you’re quitting because you believe these things you say,” he responds to Somerset in the bar, “I don’t. I think you wanna believe ‘em because you’re quitting. You want me to agree with you…but I won’t say that. I don’t agree with you. I do not. I can’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In times of hardship, it’s much easier to run away from or to join in on the misery, but we must fight it, even if it doesn’t make a difference, because someday, to somebody it will!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Princess Bride (1987)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/the-princess-bride-1987/" />
    <updated>2025-02-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/the-princess-bride-1987/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/9nmMncgn0u5u3z54Vl2k42oGDDo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Westley and Princess Buttercup silhouetted by a sunset&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In honour of today being my Mum’s 58th Birthday, I thought I would talk about one of her all time favourite films. The film permeated my entire childhood – one of our cats was even named Wes, naturally short for Westley, and while I was too young to remember most of the names of the other nine we had at the time, I’m pretty sure there was a Vizzini in their somewhere (as inconceivable as the whole thing might sound. Nowadays, we’ve made it a tradition to see it at the cinema whenever it’s been on, and as luck would have it, it’s on tonight of all nights. So, allow me to just gush about a film that has always had a place in my heart – at least for a few hundred words or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fred Savage plays a child who’s been at home with a fever. He’s hasn’t quite recovered, but he’s well enough to play &lt;em&gt;Hardball&lt;/em&gt; (1985), and he plans to make a whole day of it. That is, until his grandpa, played by &lt;em&gt;Columbo’s&lt;/em&gt; Peter Falk, comes in to surprise him with a gift: a decrepit and leather-bound romance novel. The old man soon begins reading the story, but his grandson is immediately turned off by all the schmaltz. A peasant stablehand named Westley (Cary Ewels) and the Princess Buttercup (Robin Wright) fall in love. Westley decides to leave for the high seas in search of riches and parting tragically, the lovers seal their passion with a kiss. It’s enough to make the grandson ill again, but when his grandfather tells him of Westley’s death and the hands of Dread Pirate Roberts and Buttercup’s kidnapping by the short-tempered and shrewd Vizzini (Wallace Shawn) and his band of goons, the boy is hooked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greatest thing about &lt;em&gt;The Princess Bride&lt;/em&gt; is it’s ability to straddle the line between parody and earnestness. It may have a cast of comedic actors, six fingered men and rodents of unusual size, but the expertly choreographed swordplay, characters with deeper motivations and backstories, and moments of genuine suspense – like Buttercup and Westley sinking in quicksand in the Fire Swamp – suggest a grander fairytale. The parody elements then become the grandfather’s flourishes as an unreliable narrator. As he skims a page here and skips a page there, the story no longer becomes about “twue lahv” but the power of stories themselves, and the loved ones who help create our wildest dreams. The everyday storytellers who orate their own abridged tales for our benefit, the ones who craft the memories we’ll never forget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William Goldman, the screenwriter and author of the original novel, was having special difficulty outlining Westley’s lowest moment, him being strapped to the Torture Machine, and didn’t quite know how to get him out of it. He was racking his brain trying to come up with a solution, until unconsciously, he wrote down two words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Westley dies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing those words, so concrete on the page, made him cry. Like a grieving parent, Goldman could longer live in denial about what was to happen to Westley. He may have found a way to revive Westley later on, but in that moment, like Savage’s grandson, he was left distraught at the unfairness of it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, Prince Humperdinck’s casual remarks prior about needing to miss the whole affair add a deliciously evil layer to the whole thing that’s hard not to laugh at:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Tyrone, you know how much I love watching you work, but I’ve got my country’s 500th anniversary to plan, my wedding to arrange, my wife to murder and Gilda to frame for it. I’m swamped.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s also delivered with such coolness by Chris Sarandon that it’s unnerving at the same time. The film arguably has as much staying power as it does because it loves the genre of medieval romance almost as much as it has fun laughing at its many, many tropes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In era where everything needs to be lampshaded or dripping in irony for people to be comfortable laughing at it, &lt;em&gt;The Princess Bride&lt;/em&gt; brings comedy back to a place of love and wonder and one that takes no joy in cruelly mocking its characters. Inigo Montoya for example, may be casually ribbed for his repeated practicing of how he will introduce himself to his father’s killer, but by the end, the words, “Hello. My name is Inigo Montoya. You killed my father. Prepare to die!” Becomes the battle cry of a man fighting through death to enact his greatest purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a fitting twist for the film’s production, Director Rob Reiner was given a copy of Goldman’s novel by his father when he was growing up. In a sense, the creation of the film is a love story in itself. Rob’s love for the material, and Goldman’s love for the story that brought his daughters so much joy, brought the two artists in a way neither expected. With the 1973 screenplay being shopped around as the stuff of legends (with names like Truffeau or Robert Redford previously attached to direct), the young “upstart” Reiner was the only one who was able to understand Goldman’s vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…But that’s a whole other story, and I can tell you seem annoyed. You want me to stop? Yes? &lt;em&gt;As you wish.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/wD2Bp9RIF36EfsHiVqPNLq1SEOI.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Westley defending his princess after exiting The Fireswamp&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Grand Theft Hamlet (2024)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/grand-theft-hamlet-2024/" />
    <updated>2025-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/grand-theft-hamlet-2024/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/xaqEyWfOH64ihSoTGbOKFYhcybC.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An Alien auditioning at the Vinewood Bowl&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year is 2021 and England is in it’s third lockdown during the pandemic. Sam Crane and Mark Oosterveen, two out-of-work theatre actors, spend their days together in &lt;em&gt;GTA Online&lt;/em&gt; playing slots, driving around Los Santos and gunning down innocent civilians. But the once fun and sprawling possibilities of the game have now turned into a mindless chore for Sam, whose recent responsibilities as a parent and husband have no patience for his unemployed arse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, until he discovers the Vinewood Bowl, a vacant outdoor arena in the game. Inspired to work with Mark on a production of Shakespeare’s &lt;em&gt;Hamlet&lt;/em&gt; entirely within the world of GTA, he puts on a test performance that goes about as well as you’d expect – horribly. But after Sam’s wife, documentary filmmaker Pinny Grylls, learns of her husband’s utterly insane idea, she decides to document the process, buying the game and screen recording her own character to form what we now know as &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Hamlet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to the ACMI commissioned piece &lt;em&gt;The Grannies&lt;/em&gt; – where several artists tried to reach the out-of-bounds areas of &lt;em&gt;Red Dead Redemption II&lt;/em&gt; – Sam, Mark and Pinny create a project that’s marvellously novel. The documentary creates the kind of warm feeling that only a DIY project can. Dialogue is garbled through game chat and out of sync with character’s mouths; auditions are interrupted by sudden gunfire between audience members or the police rocking up from a performed punch. What’s most remarkable, is that both the documentary – as well as Sam and Mark’s version of &lt;em&gt;Hamlet&lt;/em&gt; – is done entirely within &lt;strong&gt;the vanilla game&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve spent anytime watching livestreams in the past decade you’ve no doubt heard of GTA Role Play (RP) – even if you’ve never played the game before. It’s essentially taking the immersion of an open world or sandbox like &lt;em&gt;GTA&lt;/em&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;Garry’s Mod&lt;/em&gt; for all my Source fans out there) and applying the type of serious LARPing you’d see at a renaissance fair or DnD campaign. Players treat the world of Los Santos as the “real”; you go about your day as your character, and if you break the law, the police – usually fellow players or DMs – will arrest you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, this is done mainly on a modded instance on PC, with people who know what they’re signing up for and all on a privately owned server that can moderate and remove any undesirable griefers and stream-snipers. Sam and Mark not only play on console, but are often found rehearsing in public lobbies or matches where any number of people can show up to spoil the fun. So, the joy of the documentary becomes how exactly they are going to find players willing to cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things don’t go well at first, with their first potential actor (Co3lho) speaking little to no english and leaving after Mark’s demo soliloquy. djphil is more promising, being a literary agent who’s always wanted to be in a production of &lt;em&gt;Hamlet&lt;/em&gt; , but she soon finds herself unavailable when her nephew, whose account she was borrowing, moves away for work. Nevertheless, thanks to posting about their production on social media, complete with a chaotic in game trailer, they’re able to rally enough friends (Dipo), RP players (Nora) and even famous voice actors (Jen, Pharrah from &lt;em&gt;Overwatch&lt;/em&gt; ) to form a troupe for the play. But who really stands out to the audience are the genuine &lt;em&gt;GTA Online&lt;/em&gt; players who join the group. Passersby like ParTebMosMir comes to the audition in a gaudy alien outfit ready to mess around, but soon becomes engrossed once he observes the other performers. It’s not really the actual performances that get you, as anyone with a brain can figure out Mark thinks his soccer friend Dipo is right to play Hamlet. Instead, it’s those anonymous players who rally around the troupe that end up receiving the most love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a couple months, when the end of the pandemic seems like a possibility, Mark and Sam aren’t exactly surprised to learn that most of their cast can’t balance their “real” work with their life inside Los Santos. Their disappointment reaches an all time high, when Dipo, having been offered a job in a real production, can no longer play Hamlet. Sam begins to question why they’re continuing with the project when it’s eating up so much of their time. And while Mark admits he has nothing to go back to, he can’t help but wonder what this job is exactly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re stuck doing, this…What is it? Fake job, nonsense job? Whatever this is.” – Mark&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these darker moments are no doubt resonant with many unemployed creatives still struggling after the pandemic &lt;em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;cough, cough&lt;/em&gt;),&lt;/em&gt; that’s unfortunately where the cracks in the production start to show. Naturally, no documentary is truly candid; no matter how low budget or intentional the director is. But when Mark opens up about his aunt’s funeral and how he has no more living relatives, or Pinny chews out Sam for missing her birthday for &lt;em&gt;GTA,&lt;/em&gt; it may feel dramatically powerful, but you can smell the theatricality of it all. It’s at least made better by the intentional cut here and there to NPC’s listening in to all the filmmakers’ dirty laundry over game chat – as it shows Sam, Mark and Pinny are at the very least self aware enough to be a bit tongue-in-cheek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And all that ceases to matter entirely once the final performance kicks off. With old characters like ParTeb returning to watch, Mark acting as both narrator and tour guide, and all the mishaps that can happen on a blimp, boat or plane, happening – the excitement is palpable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What little we get of the actual &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Hamlet&lt;/em&gt; speaks to how wonderful games can be for forging lifelong friendships and that even events that seem small in the beginning can create wonderful real world memories for those willing to join in on the fun.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Annihilation (2018) – Going Where Novum Has Gone Before</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/annihilation-2018-going-where-novum-has-gone-before/" />
    <updated>2025-03-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/annihilation-2018-going-where-novum-has-gone-before/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/mrY8nJNnk9KFtn8NvWnHA8Gi1oI.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Natalie Portman, Jennifer Jason Leigh and Tuva Novotny staring a mutant croc in the mouth&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science Fiction has always been about exploring the outer reaches of our reality. And while space operas – with their many planets, diverse cultures and complex political struggles – provide an intriguing window into the future, their dominance in the genre has lead to a mess of nonsense names and information overload. While there are very few exceptions ( &lt;em&gt;The Dune Series and Original Star Wars Trilogy&lt;/em&gt; having creators who drew on real world societies or religions and stretched them to their logical conclusions) &lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; it’s hard to distinguish any grey, brutalist, starship colony from one another. Pulp Sci-Fi gets around this problem by bringing space to our own backyard or specialising in a certain science. It does this through what’s called the “Novum”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Novum, or “new thing” in Latin is the element in a science fiction story that changes everything. More precisely, it is the one changes that, as a consequence, changes everything else around it. For Denis Villeneuve’s &lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt; (2016), it could be as simple as aliens coming to earth. Yet aliens have been a staple of Sci-Fi well before author Ted Chiang decided to put pen to paper. So his “new thing” is instead considered to be their language – one which destroys the very concept of past and present. For the far older &lt;em&gt;Planet of the Apes&lt;/em&gt; (1968), it was simple as, what if monkeys were sentient instead of humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s this narrowing of focus that allows the story to be engaging, as protagonists are often forced into discovering what makes the Novum tick, and as a consequence entice danger and leave the audience intrigued about how they’ll solve the mystery. H.G Wells was the master of this form of storytelling. His inventor from &lt;em&gt;The Time Machine&lt;/em&gt; and biologist from &lt;em&gt;The Island of Doctor Moreau&lt;/em&gt; are stricken mad by their adventures before the story even starts, but it only excites us more for what horrors await when they finally have the courage to recount their tales. This is because their discoveries of time travel and animal people are the one substantial change that creates every other consequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New writers often struggle to create a believable Sci-Fi world because everything has to be “new”. New flying cars for new, modified people to drive to their new job as new testers for a new drug that makes you see a new virtual reality. Everything in their world has to have a seperate explanation for each new thing added, so their future becomes a tangled mess of generic ideas, because in an effort to unique, they struggle to balance all these new ideas in first drafts, leading to the next one being derivative so that its easier to keep track of everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Novum stories don’t have that problem because every future thing branches out from that one concept. Replicants in &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt; are robots virtually identical to humans. That one sentence leaves behind questions: What are they used for? Who created them? Who repairs them? If they think and act like humans how do we tell them apart, and if so, can they feel like us too?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer enough of these questions in a satisfying way, and you not only have a world, characters and gadgets, but their ramifications create a clear conflict within the story. As a result, they allow science fiction to be as simple or complex as the author desires – as long as it still has that central idea, people will not only follow along, but they’ll have a fun time doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s still a feet to pull all this off successfully. Because despite what J.J Abrams’ might tell you, you still need to have answers that are not only satisfying enough, but also open enough to have audience members create their own conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why I think Alex Garland’s adaptation of &lt;em&gt;Annihilation&lt;/em&gt; , and I assume Jeff VanderMeer’s original novel, is the pinnacle of a modern-day Novum story (or at least tied for first with &lt;em&gt;Arrival&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/9trZvBr44UGedUOiGo3jgSUw13e.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Natalie Portman staring down the tunnel to her doom?&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A meteor crashes into a lighthouse. Over the course of several months it emanates a oil coloured border around the surrounding area nicknamed “The Shimmer”. Designated as “The Southern Reach”, the American Government decides to study what this strange phenomenon is exactly. However, the personnel who enter disappearing, and the border soon encroaching onto to the mainland, the pursuit to discover quickly turns into an effort to destroy, as it’s existence could mean the end of life as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we first meet Lena (Natalie Portman), she’s already done the impossible and returned from The Shimmer alive. But surrounded by hazmat suited officials, we learn that she was the only one of her crew to make it. Her survival raises more questions than answers, and it’s only then that we learn what happened. After her husband and fellow army squad-mate, Kane (Oscar) reappears from a year long mission in which he was presumed to be dead, Lena is kidnapped by Area X, the government branch in charge of studying The Southern Reach, when Kane is rushed to the hospital for “radiation poisoning”. We may not know what The Shimmer is, but thanks to Garland and VanderMeer asking the right questions, we have the protagonist goal (find a way to save her husband from the effects of the shimmer), the antagonist (Area X and The Shimmer itself), as well as what awaits her if she fails (radiation sickness and the death of her and her husband).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes time for Lena and her crew to cross over to The Southern Reach, Garland borrows another of Well’s tools: the embedded narrative. When they discover an abandoned mess hall, Lena realises Kane was here before her. And when their leader, Dr Ventress (Jennifer Jason Leigh), finds an SD Card left behind by Kane and his own crew, everyone learns that the shimmer is not emitting radiation but is fundamentally changing the environment, animals and even people around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lena’s interrogation may embed the film’s story, but Kane’s story is the second layer that foreshadows what will happen to Lena’s crew. This is only possible because The Shimmer blocks contact from the outside world and those who have a story to tell are trapped inside. All of this, mind you is links back to the one element: The Shimmer and it’s so-called radiation. Radiation is able to explain everything so far, the bodily destruction of cells, the shifting of DNA to create mutations, but what it doesn’t explain is what “the one thing” is, as we already have plenty of radiation on earth, and no mutation is rapid or severe enough to cause animals, plants and humans to merge. That’s why when astrophysicist Josie (Josie Radek) figures out what it actually is, the Novum also becomes a satisfying twist in and of itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shimmer is refraction. Not just of light waves, but of everything, sound, time, cells and “all DNA”. It’s not radiation waves that are altering their DNA, but DNA itself refracting against its surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to see then why the simple notion of “what if everything could refract” spawns a million different possibilities and existential horrors. It still takes a genius to come up with questions and answers for everyone, but by focusing on one thing helps writers like Garland and Vandermere become curious and stretch their imaginations beyond what they thought was possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ironically, a Novum is powerful because it brings fiction writing down to an exact science.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Cherry Falls (2000)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/cherry-falls-2000/" />
    <updated>2025-03-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/cherry-falls-2000/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/b8KbYr4ssvlT2k1dLvJxcL55WOu.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brittany Murphy bloodied after a rough night&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that killers target sex crazed teens. Ever since Jason was left unattended at a summer camp, psychos have hunted spatially-challenged horn-dogs like they were going extinct. But what if the opposite were true? What if a murderer targeted those yet to make a move; virgins?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the killing of several of her classmates escalate tensions in the small town of Cherry Falls, Jody (Brittany Murphy) and her fellow students are left in a state of panic and confusion. But when her Dad, the overprotective Sheriff Brent (Michael Biehn, &lt;em&gt;Aliens&lt;/em&gt; ) along with the rest of the faculty discover the victims were all virgins before they died, they all scramble to do the nasty before their days are numbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exes hook back up, nerds flex their comic book knowledge on shy wall flowers, and Dad’s ask their daughter’s if they’ve done “it” yet. This kind of pandemonium is played for laughs, and it’s hilarious, although just not in the way the film probably expects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From minute one, the attempt to latch onto the &lt;em&gt;Scream Franchise&lt;/em&gt; ’s success becomes pathetically apparent. Parents coming home before to see their child murdered, a principal murdered during the daytime, and even a kidnapped Dad and well meaning but suspicious law enforcement officer combined into one. It’s twist is a mishmash of Kevin Williamson’s original 1996 film and Alfred Hitchcock’s, so if you’ve seen either and were hoping for a nice surprise, you’ll have some idea who the culprit is before Jody’s even left the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not a question of the film’s originality, as some of the best slashers were cutting and pasting what they liked from &lt;em&gt;Black Christmas&lt;/em&gt; to great effect. It’s more a question of what director, Geoffrey Wright didn’t do to elevate. As the greatest twist of this film is realising that &lt;em&gt;Metal Skin’s&lt;/em&gt; true-blue Aussie director made a bargain bin American slasher. And with it’s barely audible dialogue, complete with classroom echo and ruffled mics, it may have been a bargain to make, but it certainly is a ripoff to the ears. And with no subtitles on the official DVD, it just goes to show how much the distributor, much less the director cared about their “masterful” writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s not all bad, in fact, it’s a fun time with mates because it’s bad. When it jumps discordantly to &lt;em&gt;Matrix-esque&lt;/em&gt; chase scenes and gaudy early naughties special effects, or cuts to it’s cheap wigs or rubbery props, you can’t help but feel giddy. And at the very least, Wright knows how to do some interesting set-pieces now and again. Like the real stunt driving at the climax of &lt;em&gt;Metal Skin,&lt;/em&gt; when the killer interrupts the high school orgy at the end of &lt;em&gt;Cherry Falls&lt;/em&gt; , a herd of half nude students clamber down the stairs to escape, only to stampede the poor female officer attempting to apprehend him, in what is one of the only kills I’ve seen in a slasher that doesn’t directly involve the main killer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But besides those big moments, it doesn’t really have its own identity, and that’s made more insulting when more serious topics are turned into cartoonish spectacles to “shock”. Other horrors, even meta ones like &lt;em&gt;Scream,&lt;/em&gt; treat these traumas seriously. Sidney’s whole arc is predicated on the idea that while we get to home after the credits roll, Ghost-face’s actions with live with her and the rest of his surviving victims long after. Wright will often try to do something similar, but often mishandles or heightens the drama to the point of slapstick. He gets that horror is supposed to be a fun thrill, but often forgets why we confront those horrors on screen in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, did I have fun? Yeah absolutely. Do I think it’s a good film? Absolutely not. With the constant stream of slashers that I floating around there, I think it’s a interesting exercise into what producers mean when they say, “That’s great! But can you make it like this other thing?” A guilty pleasure for sure, but only with a buddy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when I’m watching movies, there’s always room for one more – ; ) .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/3XeVjLdzCBxBA0eK1mhQIYVZqkw.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brittany Murphy staring up at the ceiling of her bedroom&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hundreds of Beavers (2022)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/hundreds-of-beavers-2022/" />
    <updated>2025-04-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/hundreds-of-beavers-2022/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/tPoEiQnxGLjJ6uhiut8aTvuC0YH.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ryland Brickson Cole Tews and his nervous beaver lawyer in beaver court&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d been waiting to see Mike Cheslik’s magnum opus for about two years now, and heard it hyped up at festivals for twice as long. So, when I was finally able to see it with my own eyes — in a packed cinema no less — you bet I was excited. But was the praise warranted, and did I maybe have my hopes just a little too high? Luckily, it was just as good as they say. &lt;em&gt;Hundreds of Beavers&lt;/em&gt; isn’t just a love letter to Cartoons and silent-era slapstick, it’s a goddamned renaissance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Jean Kayak (Ryland Brickson Cole Tews) and his cider brewery go up in smoke thanks to some rogue beavers — their gnawing of the largest barrel culminating in a mass fire to his apple orchard and an explosion that heralds in an ice age for the surrounding wilderness — the young man is forced to survive a harsh and unforgiving winter. Having no success with his harebrained schemes to catch and stew a couple of rabbits, and his well endowed snowmen struggling to help him catch and fry any fish, he succumbs to the hunger and cold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not before being rescued just in nick of time. Picked up just in time by the jolly Master Fur Trapper (Wes Tank) and his sleigh of hounds, Jean accompanies the Christ(mas)-like figure to drop off his sack of animal pelts to his friend and patron, the grizzled Merchant (Doug Mancheski). And it’s there where Jean meets the prettiest woman alive, The Furrier (Olivia Graves). However, learning that her hand in marriage belongs to the Master fur Trapper, and that her father is loathsome and hard to please Merchant, Jean makes it his mission to become a Fur Trapper worthy of the old man’s praise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/d26hVZhft7XCwkpVqZBoRSu20IR.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ryland Brickson Cole Tews being chased down by the titular hundreds of beavers&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film really is something you just have to see to believe it, but Cheslik goes above and beyond what you’d expect a live action rubber-hose cartoon to look like. The Merchant will squash a stretch his face with displeasure as he spits ink coloured tobacco toward a spittoon, only to miss it in increasingly comical ways each time. Era accurate lighting will obscure Jean’s face as he skulks around the beavers’ elaborate lair, and wide lensed close-ups exaggerate every characters’ already distinct features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s not to mention the wonderfully nostalgic sound design. Despite being a relatively silent film, special care is taken to give every character a unique voice. Crisply dubbed and bursting with energy, every shout, cry, swear and cheer adds a layer on top of the already expressive body language of its actors, to make even the most hardened critics chuckle. Combined with old school foley techniques and the Merrie Melodies of Chris Ryan, &lt;em&gt;Hundreds of Beavers&lt;/em&gt; is no doubt looney.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it also dances to its own tune, and with a score of other influences from video games to modern internet humour, it’s easy to see why. Because the film establishes itself as an expert of the form, it’s breaking away from tradition produces the most laughs. When the Furrier skins Jean’s first kill, the doting music, her lighthearted giggles and his swooning over her are all funny in their own right. But when blood splatters, organs squelch and A deflated raccoon’s plush innards spill out onto the table, it induces a slight shock in the audience. It’s Cheslik’s ability to escalate — escalate jokes, plot points and obstacles — that keeps feeling repetitive. It’s says something when a movies has more bits than beavers, and I still walked away wanting more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The VFX work, while simple is shockingly competent for this level of production. The green screening of people is not only clean but flawless. A manipulated leg here or there is nothing compared to the lack of haloing or artifacts that even multimillion dollar productions struggle to iron out. It’s film emulation is enough to fool even the most analogue filmmakers unless you know what to look for, and the aforementioned lighting is stunning to look at from a technical standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really, &lt;em&gt;Hundreds of Beavers&lt;/em&gt; is a testament to time, passion and commitment. Anyone willing to write about the patience it takes for a man to trap thousands of cunning animals certainly isn’t a director riding trends and hurrying out slop. In an age where studios are touting 300 million plus budgets while giving none of it to their rushed and tired VFX staff, and even channels like Corridor Digital, who have the talent and resources necessary to make incredible proof of concepts, but whose algorithm dictates quick two second google searches, one week turnarounds, and dabbling with AI, make the otherwise passionate team unable to think outside the bounds of a clickable thumbnail, it’s nice to see that Cheslik doesn’t just know his stuff — he lives and breathes it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>MIFF — Chain Reactions (2024)</title>
    <link href="https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/miff-chain-reactions-2024/" />
    <updated>2025-08-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://finnwritesmovies.com/posts/miff-chain-reactions-2024/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/original/4h1W80H4P0lJrzwp61ggD1m5JGr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Marilyn Burns hysterical on five different prints of the Texas Chain Saw Massacre&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While my first experience seeing Leatherface wasn&#39;t in Fangoria, it &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; in a film magazine. My older cousin had brought it up with him to one of our regular trips to the family cabin. Flicking the through the pages, his was the first face (or faces?) that caught my eye. His skin sallowed from the glossy paper of the film mag appeared alongside other horror icons like Jason, Freddy and Billy the Puppet, but where the others had this goofy and cartoonish charm in my child mind, Leatherface truly disturbed me. Wearing the skin of your victim was such a ghoulish thing to my nine year old mind that I felt like his low placement on &amp;quot;The 100 Most Evil Villains&amp;quot; listicle must have been a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gaffney&#39;s Creek, as it turned out, became the regular spot for friends and family to chat about our horrorful fancies. With a population total of five, no reception and a single phone booth several kilometres away, our shack was (and still is) the ideal slasher location. Once, when my friend came up with my brother and I, we joked that Jason would take the woodcutter’s axe in the corner of our room and hack us to bits in our sleep. Ah the innocent daydreams of ten year olds!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all have stories like this. Whether its Patton Oswalt being sent to a 19th century nightmare world through &lt;em&gt;Nosferatu&lt;/em&gt; (1922) on his family&#39;s beat-up projector, or famed author Stephen King, high on painkillers, begging his son to turn off &lt;em&gt;The Blair Witch&lt;/em&gt; (1999) on his hospital TV: horror has made a deep impression on us all. And no film has come close to sawing its way through our collective brainstem than Tobe Hooper&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Texas Chain Saw Massacre&lt;/em&gt; (1974). A now fifty year old urban legend that only strengthens with the degradation of its many film prints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Director Alexandre O. Philippe uses &lt;em&gt;Chain Reactions&lt;/em&gt; as a springboard to not only gush about Hooper&#39;s magnum opus, but to interview five of his fellow afflicted. Part of the fun of these five distinct interviews is being surprised by his choices. Enlightened by their by their takes and experiences with the film (or its contemporaries), it’s nerve wracking to find out which celebrity might be lurking around the corner to give their two cents. You&#39;ve got your obvious picks like King or horror scholar and Melbourne critic Alexandra Heller-Nicholas, to wildcards like Oswalt, who at first seems to be an excuse to use his stand-up on movie titles as a cold open, but whose knowledge of the film and obsessive analysis of it&#39;s every frame is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/09/04/the-poetic-work-of-trailer-recutters&quot;&gt;well documented&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standout for me though was Takashi Miike, whose torturously grotesque films like &lt;em&gt;Audition&lt;/em&gt; (2000) and &lt;em&gt;Ichi the Killer&lt;/em&gt; (2001) would probably be screwball comedies if the then thirteen year old director hadn&#39;t been turned out of a Chaplin screening and decided to see what else was on instead. What surprised me, as I imagine it will surprise most, is that Miike&#39;s sadistic fancies are far from apathetic. He finds violence that&#39;s solely used as a &amp;quot;tool for filmmaking&amp;quot; sickening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to be a common sentiment among the other guests, as well as Philippe himself. There are multiple mentions of the &lt;em&gt;Death Wish&lt;/em&gt; series of films throughout the documentary, as many consider the films to be the purest form of violence being &#39;glorified’. As Charles Bronson guns down disenfranchised drug dealers and loiterers, his life as an enforcer is given a puritanical sheen by &lt;em&gt;Death Wish’s&lt;/em&gt; filmmakers. This is in stark contrast to Miike and Hooper, who intentionally create moments of dementedness that make you squirm, writhe and want to turn away from the disgusting hyper-violence exposed to your eyeballs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If pain and fear are two of the strongest feelings we have as humans, it makes no sense for Hooper to be senseless. After all, Hooper wouldn’t have been able to scare others so effectively if he wasn’t frightened by his own ideas in the first place. To paraphrase Karyn Kusama and Oswalt’s observations, Hooper was scared shitless by the U.S&#39; oncoming insanity, the rise of the serial killer, gun culture and the distorted lie that was to become the American family. A madness that would rise over the land like a boiling red sun, subsuming the land in a confused and apathetic sadism. Leatherface and his ecletic family&#39;s cannibalism were just an extension of our collective disconnection from reality, from others and from ourselves. &lt;em&gt;Texas Chain Saw Massacre&lt;/em&gt; is Hooper&#39;s American nightmare made manifest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Phillipe does an excellent job dragging us and his guests into that nightmare, with never before seen on set footage that rises from the ashes with a jaw dropping 4K scan. Cameras walk through the empty hallways and float up creaky wooden steps without a soul in sight. Spliced in with footage from the film, these out of time shots haunt the every frame, even more than &lt;em&gt;Texas Chain Saw&lt;/em&gt; itself. They become spectral afterimages of a filmmaker long gone from this mortal coil. These images complement the meaty interviews, and strangely, provide quite a few sight gags. When a gleeful, shirtless and diapered toddler waddles through skulls and chicken bones, kicking up feathers in his wake, it&#39;s a surreal look into the onset fun that was had while filming one of the scariest movies of all time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s fun sharing a nightmare with others, because it means we&#39;re unlikely to go mad if we know things can still scare us and others. But while it is interesting to see your horror favs were once scared little children as well, I wouldn&#39;t mind seeing who that kid ended up being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is he still playing in viscera with same tenacity as someone fooling around in autumn leaves or is just working some random desk job?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What sort of nightmares did he end up crafting?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thanks for Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Decided this would be the perfect film to help revive the blog. They’ll be more MIFF stuff on the way so stay tuned!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And remember if you dear reader want to make a request on what I review next, you can always shoot me a gold coin donation over on Ko-fi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>